<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A demonstration of the resurrection of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ; and therein of the Christian religion. Very usefull for the further satisfaction and confirmation of all good Christians; as likewise for the confutation and conviction of those that have a Jewish or atheisticall spirit in them. / Written by Richard Garbutt, Bachelour in Divinity, sometimes fellow of Sydney Colledge in Cambridge, and afterwards preacher of the Gospel at Leeds in Yorshire [sic].</title>
            <author>Garbutt, Richard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 210 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 97 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85735</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G207</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1693_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202150</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862546</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862546</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114709</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85735)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114709)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 211:E1693[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A demonstration of the resurrection of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ; and therein of the Christian religion. Very usefull for the further satisfaction and confirmation of all good Christians; as likewise for the confutation and conviction of those that have a Jewish or atheisticall spirit in them. / Written by Richard Garbutt, Bachelour in Divinity, sometimes fellow of Sydney Colledge in Cambridge, and afterwards preacher of the Gospel at Leeds in Yorshire [sic].</title>
                  <author>Garbutt, Richard.</author>
                  <author>Jackson, Nathaniel, d. 1662.</author>
                  <author>Cartwright, Christopher, 1602-1658.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 168 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Samuel Gellibrand, at the Ball in Pauls Churchyard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657. [i.e. 1656]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Editor's dedication signed: Nathaniel Jackson.</note>
                  <note>Introduction signed: Chr. Cartwright.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb: 23"; the 7 in the imprint date has been crossed out and replaced with a "6".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Resurrection --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Jesus Christ --  History of doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114709:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DEMONSTRATION OF THE RESURRECTION Of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt; And therein of the Chriſtian RELIGION.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Very uſefull</hi> For the further ſatisfaction and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of all good <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> AS LIKEWISE For the confutation and convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of thoſe that have a <hi>Jewiſh</hi> or <hi>Atheiſticall</hi> ſpirit in them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>WRITTEN</hi> By RICHARD GARBUTT, Bachelour in Divinity, ſometimes fellow of <hi>Sydney</hi> Colledge in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards Preacher of the Goſpel at <hi>Leeds</hi> in <hi>Yorſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Gellibrand,</hi> at the <hi>Ball</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi> Churchyard. 165<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:114709:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114709:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Rev. &amp; Clar. Viro, DOMINO,</hi> RICHARDO MINSHULL S. S. Theologiae Doctori, &amp; Collegii Sydn. apud Cantabrigienſes Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctori vigilantiſſimo, nec non Sociis, atque adeò univerſae ejuſdem Collegii Societati. S.P.D. harum lucubratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Editor.</head>
            <p>DEmonſtratio haec (Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verende Doctor, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſsimi Socii, &amp; lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae
<pb facs="tcp:114709:3"/>indolis Adoleſcentuli) vos inſalutatos praeterire non de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buit. Collegium veſtrum bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos aluit Garbuttos, non minus diſpares, quam <hi>Rebeccae</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melli. Senior quidem eorum haec ſcripſit, ut &amp; alia multa prelo ſatis digna, digna quae &amp; perlegantur, &amp; relegantur; quorum nonnulla ſaltem noſtrâ opellâ obſtetricante brevi fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras emittentur. Praeterquam enim quod dolendum eſt, ea publico tamdiu caruiſſe, adeo mihi ſapiunt, ut memet tenere non queam, quin ederem. Quod eò alacriùs &amp; confidentiùs ſum facturus, modo vos, alii<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que
<pb facs="tcp:114709:3"/>docti piique mibi fueritis incitamento.</p>
            <p>Agite, gaudeamus invicem in Garbutto noſtro et veſtro. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum dico, quia Noſtras fuit, &amp; in publicâ Scholâ<note n="*" place="margin">Vulgò <hi>Cuckold</hi> aliàs. <hi>Cox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woll.</hi>
               </note> Cox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voldiae informatus, ad tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus uſque quo Academia Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabrigienſis eum in gremium ſuum exciperet; admiſſus au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem veſtrae Societatis parieti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, per totos viginti annos adhaeſit; Quibus quantam multiplicis literaturae, cum gratiâ Dei bene conditae, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem congeſsit; teſtari poſſunt provectioris aetatis Theologi, atteſtatur &amp; hoc opuſculum,
<pb facs="tcp:114709:4"/>&amp; quae ſuperſunt alia, eximia certè monumenta rationis, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genii, judicii, induſtriae, &amp; pietatis non vulgarium.</p>
            <p>Quicquid <hi>Garbutti</hi> eſt, olet Lampada, olit S. Spiritum. Quare meritò pro veſtro ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicare poſsitis. Aſt ſecundâ vice Noſter fit, poſtquam e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim vos reliquit, agrum Ebo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racenſem repetiit, &amp; in Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicipio<note n="*" place="margin">Vulgò Leeds.</note> 
               <hi>Leedenſi,</hi> noſtrae Paroeciae <hi>Barvicienſi</hi> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guo (ipſo gurgite Mercaturae in tractu hujus Comitatûs Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentali) conſedit,<note n="*" place="margin">Vulgò Barwicke.</note> ibique in officio ſuo valdè ſedulus per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſit uſque dum — ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras
<pb facs="tcp:114709:4"/>evaſit ad auras Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus —</p>
            <p>Quare duplici nomine No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum eſſe quis ibit inficias?</p>
            <p>Tam clarum fuit <hi>Homeri</hi> nomen, ut multae <hi>Graeciae</hi> Ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes certatim ſibi vindicarent. Secundum diſtichon illud Grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum, quod eâ de re apud <hi>A. Gellum</hi> extat.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.<note place="margin">Lib. 3. Cap. 11. Idem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatur Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero pro Arch.</note>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </q>
            <p>At quam amica noſtra conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio; ſic enim noſtram requiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus partem, ut vobis veſtram liberè relinquamus intactam, nec invidemus. Imò charitas
<pb facs="tcp:114709:5"/>(quae regulam hanc, <hi>Bonum quò communiùs, eò me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liùs,</hi> nobis ſubminiſtrat) <hi>Garbuttum</hi> Noſtrum &amp; Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum omnibus communem ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibgre nos jubet. Sic gratiam ineamus cum aliis, &amp; Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam Manum Optimorum, id<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſine minimo noſtro diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio, nobis demerebimur. Et quid eſt quod mihi malim? Hoc idem, Sol Aſtrorum prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps, nos monet; nobis enim non ideo minus gratus oritur, quia toti laetus illuceſcit Orbi. Impingit forſan aliquis ad ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulum Libelli, autumans prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipium hoc (Chriſtum Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rexiſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:114709:5"/>&amp;c.) credi oportere, demonſtrari non poſſe: Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minibus, id genus, refellendis (modo pertinaces non ſint) nullis meis argumentis opus eſt, ſufficit unicus hic Codicu. lus, ubi non ſolum Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionem Chriſti, ſed &amp; S. Scripturae autoritatem, imò totius Chriſtianae Religionis veritatem inviolabiliter ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuminat. Haec enim tria adeò indivulsè cohaerent, ut nullatenus ſejungi queant.</p>
            <p>Ante viginti &amp; ſex annos <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> nobis ereptus <hi>Garbuttus,</hi> horrendas opinio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, hoc ſeculo (omnium Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctarum
<pb facs="tcp:114709:6"/>feraci) renaſcituras praeſenſiſſe videatur: ſi au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ad ſummam aetatem per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vixiſſet, quantus Malleus Haereticorum exſtitiſſet, quam commodè fanaticorum Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſmos evacuaſſet, et arma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos eorum Gigantes humi proſtraſſet, detrudendos de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum<note n="*" place="margin">In Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hennam ſecundum interpret. J. Mede in Prov. 21.16.</note> in domum <hi>Rephaim,</hi> utcunque hoc ipſum,</p>
            <p>Poſt ſua manſurum fata ſuperſtes opus magno erit uſui, Et ſic per me ab alio poſteritati ſervitur.</p>
            <p>Breve aliquod ſpecimen vitae et mortis Authoris pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre delibero, quod, inſtar
<pb facs="tcp:114709:6"/>ſpeculi ejus, (viri verè inſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis) imaginem quadantenus repreſentet; et ſane nullam in re ullâ praebuit impingendi cauſam, ne vituperetur Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterium, ſed in omnibus ſe approbavit ut Dei Miniſtrum, etc.</p>
            <p>Quam neceſſarii ſunt hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſmodi tractatus, et cogentia argumenta hâc Aetate faecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentâ, quâ Anglia noſtra (proh dolor) non ſolum in ſentinam vitiorum, ſed et officinam er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m omnium converſa eſt indigniſsimè, omnes, (iis ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lummodo, quorum Religio, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtar tabi, putruit, exceptis) ſatis vident et dolent.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:114709:7"/>
            <p>Sed manum de Tabulâ, &amp; vos ſolvo à me legendo, properate ad Authorem. Deus Opt. Max. utramque Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miam omni benedictionum ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere cumulet, &amp; quam diutiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimè ſalvas et florentes conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet, ſic precatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Veſtri ſtudioſiſſimus &amp; totius ſtatus Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demici Cupien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſimus, NATHANIEL JACKSON.</signed>
               <note place="margin">Dat. Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viciae in Elmett, Septem. 12. A. D. 1656.</note>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:114709:7"/>
            <p>THeſe Sermons here enſuing ſpeak the Authour a man both of a ſolid head, and of a ſincere heart; both of great judgment, and of good affections. They mind me of that of <hi>Cyprian, Lo here, that which is rather powerfull,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Accipe non diſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, ſed for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia. <hi>Cypr. ad Donat. Epiſ. 2.</hi> Fulmina erant lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guae ſingula verba tuae. <hi>Gerhard. loc. com. de Miniſt. Eccleſ. 5. 123.</hi> Aculeos in anim is Auditorum reliquit.</note> 
               <hi>then eloquent.</hi> And of <hi>Melanch: ons</hi> verſe, which (as <hi>Gerhard</hi> relates) he made upon the ſight of <hi>Luthers</hi> picture, <hi>Every word of thine was a thunderbolt.</hi> Surely the words of this Authour have weight in them; they do not tickle the eare, but they affect the heart: And (as it was ſaid of <hi>Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> the Athenian Oratour) they leave a ſting behind them in thoſe that heare or reade them. Such force of argument, ſuch ſtrength of reaſon, ſuch convincing demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I have ſeldome ſeene. Theſe are ſtrong lines indeed, not as to the ſound of words, but as to the ſenſe of matter. Pity it is, that
<pb facs="tcp:114709:8"/>any thing of this Authour (humane frailties excepted) ſhould dye with him. So I judg both by theſe, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sermons of his that I have ſeen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>CHR. CARTWRIGHT.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:114709:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> have peruſed this enſuing Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and though my approbation be not of that weight &amp; value as to add the leaſt grain of allowance or acceptance to this or any other the like performance, yet being requeſted to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver my opinion of it, I could not but ſay thus much, that the learned and pious Author hath herein (at leaſt to my apprehenſion) approved him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 2 Tim. 2 8</note> 
               <hi>a workman that needed not be aſhamed,</hi> yea<note n="*" place="margin">Cor. 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>a wiſe Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>builder</hi> in the Church of God, as having very ſolidly and judiciouſly ſtated and aſſerted that grand funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall article, the main pillar in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed of our Chriſtian faith, our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Chriſts Reſurrection; the truth whereef he hath undeniably prov'd and demonſtrated, as well by invincible arguments, and ſtrength of reaſon, as alſo clear and evident teſtimonies and texts of Scripture; and that both for the further confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation
<pb facs="tcp:114709:9"/>of all true Chriſtians, and the fuller conviction of all gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayers, whether Atheiſticall, Jewiſh, or Hereticall Spirits. And truly I do not remember to have ſeen ſo much Scripture and reaſon, better improv'd in ſo narrow a compaſs, nor more artificially enterwoven and twiſted together, and helping one another by a mutuall compliance, for the ſtrengthening and ſupport of ſo ſubſtantiall a truth. In a word, I look upon the Treatiſe, as verifying and performing exactly, what it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes in the Title, if not more: It being a * moſt perfect and complete Demonſtration,<note place="margin">Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratio po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſima.</note> or rather, a twofold Demonſtration, as Logicians diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, the one proving the thing<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>that</hi> it was ſo, the other the finall cauſe or end <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>why</hi> it was ſo; the one cleering the truth and reality of it as in it ſelf, the other declaring the fruit and benefit of it as to believers; the one in the former, the other in the latter Point or Obſervation. And in both theſe the Authour ſhows himſelf to have been a man ſingularly well
<pb facs="tcp:114709:9"/>skill'd both in the Theory and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of true Chriſtianity, of an able head and an honeſt heart, of a ſtrong brain, and a gratious ſpirit; The Doctrinall part of the Diſcourſe being not more ſolid and ſinewy in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming the truth, and ſettling and informing the judgment, then the Practicall, wholſom and ſavoury in ſpeaking to the conſcience, and preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing holineſs and purity of life, and the power of godlineſs. In which regard I heartily recommend the peruſall of it to all good and ſober Chriſtians, eſpecially in theſe wave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, warping, and back-ſliding times, wherein ſo many have degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated and<note n="*" place="margin">Turned Apoſtate <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 1 Tim. 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>departed from the faith, giving heed to ſeducing ſpirits,</hi> and<note n="*" place="margin">2 Pet. 3.17.</note> 
               <hi>being led away with the errour of the wicked, have fallen from their own ſtedfaſtneſs:</hi> and (I conceive) for want of thorow conviction, and ſound inſtruction in theſe main fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall truths of the Goſpel.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>JAMES DUPORT.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:114709:10"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Wondred not when I met with thoſe expreſſions of holy triumphing in <hi>Gregory Nyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Greg. Nyſ. Orat. 5. de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Id Orat. 1. de Reſur. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Cyril. Hier. Catech. 14.</note> 
               <hi>let us extol the Reſurrection of the Conqueror, the joy of the world, the life of all Nations, ſince</hi> (as he elegantly tells us) <hi>the Divell, our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer gaping to devour the bait of Chriſts fleſh when he dyed, was ſtruck through, and caught with the hook of Chriſts Divinity when he aroſe from the dead,</hi> and (as <hi>Cyril</hi> expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it) <hi>he who by ſuffering was free among the dead, by riſing again manifeſted, that he both could and would free the living.</hi> The aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of this bleſſed truth is the noble ſubject of this learned Treatiſe. I wiſh I might have been allowed, the ſecret taſting of its Divine deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacies
<pb facs="tcp:114709:10"/>without proclaiming to the world, how well I relliſh'd them, and the rather becauſe this excellent diſcourſe is as far from <hi>wanting,</hi> as are our ſlight pamphlets from <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving</hi> Commendation. Tis too low an Expreſſion to ſay this work <hi>deſerves</hi> my prayſes (worth of a <hi>mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle</hi> ſize may be ſo commended) I rather judg that my prayſes are not worthy of it, and may hope that my teſtimony will rather finde acceptance from it, than it from my Commendation. When firſt it came to my hands, it found me in ſuch a croud of buſineſs, that I hardly could finde time to <hi>begin</hi> the reading thereof; but truly when I had once begun to peruſe it, I as hardly knew how to make an <hi>end</hi> of reading, till I came to the end of the book, with ſuch an honeſt delight did it rob me of the thoughts of my other em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments; and yet neither muſt I call it a <hi>robbery,</hi> it was but a <hi>change,</hi> and that an <hi>advantageous</hi> one, for it brought me more benefit, by its peruſal, than I parted with by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing
<pb facs="tcp:114709:11"/>for a time my other read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; And (reader,) I aſſure my ſelf, if thou art a friend to Chriſt and thy ſelf, thou canſt not but with ſweeteſt contentment, view the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation of thy deareſt Lord and Maſter in <hi>his</hi> Reſurrection, and thereby thine <hi>own</hi> from the grave both of ſin and earth, ſo clearly and fully demonſtrated.</p>
            <p>The Authour of this Treatiſe I never knew, and he is now above the reſentment of earthly Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, and therefore tentation I had none, either by receiving or expecting any friendſhip from him, to ſpeak ſo freely of his book: but might I (dear Chriſtian) prevail with thee to read, love, and live the truths thereof, all that good is ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesfully obteyned, which is (I truſt) ſincerely endeavoured by the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of thy ſervant for thy Souls good,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>WILL. JENKYN, <hi>Paſtor of Black-fryers London.</hi>
               </signed>
               <date>
                  <hi>Nov.</hi> 27. 1656.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:114709:11"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>BEing deſired to peruſe this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Treatiſe concerning the Reſurrection of Chriſt, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe my thoughts of it, though my teſtimony can adde nothing to the worth of it, and very little to its ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance in the world, yet the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent contexture of Scripture, and reaſon, which I have found in it, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires me not onely to approve it, but commend it. The ſubject treated on is that of higheſt concernment, the great pillar of our faith &amp; hope, as the great Apoſtle argues <hi>1 Cor. 15.</hi> and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of handling it is in good meaſure anſwerable to the weight, and worth of its ſubject. Some may poſſibly think that this great article of faith needs no Demonſtration; And I have ſometimes been of that conceipt, that ſome principles, were ſo cleare, they needed no confirming, and ſome opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions ſo abſurd, they needed no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futing; but I find my ſelf deceived;
<pb facs="tcp:114709:12"/>for in theſe dayes wherein our lot is fallen, there is no truth ſo cleare and fundamentall, but it meets with them that doubt it, and deny it; and no errour ſo ridiculous, and unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, but finds them that will em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace and maintaine it. Therefore I cannot but judge the publiſhing of this worke very ſeaſonable, both for confirming the faith of believers (for faith deſpiſes not reaſon but makes much of it, ſo long as it keeps its place) and alſo for convincing of Atheiſts, and unbelievers, with whom it deals upon their own terms; viz: thoſe of reaſon; and in this tot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering age declining ſo faſt to Scepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſme, and Atheiſme, there is need of both. But I will not deteine the reader from the worke it ſelfe, which will beſt ſpeake for it ſelfe, wiſhing every Chriſtian a rationall and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duciall knowledge of the truth, and an experimentall knowledge of Chriſts Reſurrection.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>EDW. BOWLES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114709:12"/>
            <head>A DEMONSTRATION OF THE Reſurrection of Chriſt.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>1 Cor. 15.20.</bibl>
                  <p>But now is Chriſt riſen from the dead, the firſt fruits of them that ſlept.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>CORINTH was a famous Church, if any other, plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Apoſtle himſelf, reſiding among them a whole yeare and an halfe, for the preaching and ſetling of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel;<note place="margin">Acts 18.24.</note> and afterwards watered by <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollo an Eloquent man, and mighty in the Scriptures:</hi> but though it were thus planted, thus watered, yet not many years after there crept in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114709:13"/>abuſes into that Church, for the reforming whereof <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſpends moſt of this Epiſtle; and the two chiefe abuſes, a dangerous ſchiſme, and a dangerous hereſy. He picks out purpoſely one to be medled with firſt of all, and the other laſt of all; becauſe things ſpoken firſt and laſt take beſt impreſſion; and nothing he deſired to take deeper impreſſion, then dehortation from <hi>ſchiſme,</hi> and <hi>haereſy;</hi> the one brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the bond of charity, the other the bond of faith. Their <hi>ſchiſme,</hi> that one ſaid he was of <hi>Paul,</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Apollo,</hi> another of <hi>Cephas,</hi> another of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is confuted thorowout the four firſt chapters; Their <hi>hereſy,</hi> that ſome among them <hi>denyed the reſurrection,</hi> is with great vehemency and contention of reaſoning confuted thorowout his fifteeth Chapter: and good cauſe that the Apoſtle ſhould ſo beſtirre himſelf in confirming the doctrine of the reſurrection, it being the very knot and tye of all Religion, and all Religion falling aſunder without it;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114709:13"/>deny the Reſurrection, and the world would ſoone be as bad as hell it ſelf; if the dead riſe not again, let us eat and drinke for to morrow we dye; but affirme the Reſurrection, and beleeve it perfectly aright, and the world would be almoſt as holy as Heaven it ſelfe.<note place="margin">Acts 24.15.16.</note> 
               <hi>My hope towards God is that there ſhall be a Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the dead, both of juſt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, and herein do I exerciſe my ſelfe, to have alwayes a conſcience void of offence towards God and towards men;</hi> therefore good reaſon that the Apoſtle ſhould ſo beſtirre him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf about this point <hi>The Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the dead is the Chriſtians confidence.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fiducis Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrectio mortuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum: Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tull.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now he proves the Reſurrection, <hi>firſt</hi> more directly by plaine argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments unto the 35. verſ. Secondly, more indirectly and underhand by anſwering the ſurmiſed doubts that might be againſt it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But ſome will ſay, How are the dead raiſed up,</hi> &amp;c? This <hi>how</hi> is not an <hi>how</hi> of enquiry, (for then he ſhould not have anſwered, <hi>thou
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114709:14"/>foole;</hi> but <hi>thou curious fellow:</hi>) but an <hi>how</hi> of objection againſt the very matter; <hi>How,</hi> how is it poſſible that the dead putrified body ſhould riſe again, that every one ſhould have his own body; being eaten perhaps of the beaſts, or the fiſh, or the fowle, and turned into their ſubſtance? how alſo is it conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent that theſe vile bodyes of ours that were nothing but clogs and troubles to us here, ſhould be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to us? and this is the implyed Objection; How are the dead rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which the Apoſtle anſwers in all the parts of it, ſhewing it <hi>firſt,</hi> not to be <hi>impoſſible,</hi> becauſe wee ſee the like dayly in the ſeed ſowne, it dyes and quickens again; and alſo no feare of the impoſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty becauſe it is God that doth it: and cannot he reſtore the body, and the ſame body too? he can tell how to ſever the fleſh of men from the fleſh of beaſts; <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And <hi>ſecondly,</hi> he ſhewes it not to be <hi>inconvenient,</hi> becauſe it ſhall be the ſame body for ſubſtance, yet not for irkſome
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:114709:14"/>conditions; but as celeſtial and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtriall bodies differ a great deale for glory and excellency, ſo it from it ſelf, dying and being raiſed up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; It is ſowne in corruption, it is raiſed in incorruption; and in ſhewing this glorious change, (thereby anſwering the ſurmiſed objection of inconvenience) he ſpends moſt of the reſt of this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from the fortyeth verſe unto the end.</p>
            <p>Now for the direct proofe of the Reſurrection in the former part of the Chapter, it beares it ſelfe eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially upon this argument. That Chriſt is riſen, and therefore we ſhall riſe again too: and after that he hath a long time toſſed and tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed and waved and argued it up and down with a great deale of zeale, that Chriſt is undoubtedly riſen, (for it is the thing that he is long and earneſt about, and troubles him moſt) the other, That we ſhould therefore undoubtedly riſe, would eaſily follow, none would much gainſay it. After therefore he hath
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114709:15"/>ſo belaboured the point of Chriſts Reſurrection, thereby to inferre ours; in my text, he caſts up the ſumme of all, ſhewing what all his former reaſoning had amounted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, namely to this to tall, <hi>But now is Chriſt riſen from the dead,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>There are two things,
<list>
                  <item>Firſt, <hi>That Chriſt is riſen.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Secondly, Not ſo onely, but ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen as <hi>The firſt fruits,</hi> to ſanctify and hallow unto his father all the faithfull that ſleep in Chriſt, aſſuring them by his Reſurrection, of their bleſſed Reſurrection at laſt too. As the whole harveſt was bleſſed and ſanctified and halloved in a little handfull of the firſt fruits dedicated to God, that bleſſed and hallowed the whole harveſt; ſo Chriſts Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection bleſſeth and warrants all ours.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And Firſt, <hi>That Chriſt is riſen;</hi> But what, you will ſay, needs any proving of this point? There are no Painims here to deny the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, there are no <hi>Thomaſſes</hi> here to doubt of it, we all beleeve the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114709:15"/>of the Creed, The third day he roſe again from the dead?</p>
            <p>Beloved, I would it were ſo; but let me tell you what our Saviour ſaith,<note place="margin">Luke 18.8.</note> 
               <hi>When the ſon of man cometh ſhall he find faith on the earth?</hi> and what S. Paul ſaith,<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 3.2. Non om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium eſt fides.</note> 
               <hi>all man have not faith;</hi> to beleeve that Chriſt by his Reſurrection is the Reſurrection and life to others, is a matter that may well have a, <hi>Beleeveſt thou this?</hi> ſet upon the head of it; let me tell you, it is not for nought that the Goſpels every one of them are ſo large in the Demonſtration of the truth of Chriſts Reſurrection, by variety of circumſtances, and varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of apparitions, and that the Acts are written in effect for no other end, as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> wel obſerves, (Hom. 1.) then to prove Chriſts Reſurrection by his powerfull ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the holy Holy Ghoſt, by his powerfull endowing them with gifts of miracles, with gifts of a more then man-like courage and forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, to preach ſtoutly the Goſpell notwithſtanding all oppoſition, by
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114709:16"/>the glorious ſucceſſe likewiſe in their preaching, to convert ſo many of the Jews,<note place="margin">Act. 6.7.</note> even a great company of prieſts themſelves; and ſuch numbers of the gentiles unto the faith; theſe ſpeake the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, theſe are not the works of one that lyeth in the power of death.</p>
            <p>Let me tell you, there is more in that of S. Paul then every one thinks, <hi>If thou confeſſe with thy mouth the Lord Jeſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10.9.</note> 
               <hi>and ſhalt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve in thy heart that God hath raiſed him from the dead, thou ſhalt be ſaved;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let me tell you further, that the paucity of good livers ſhews plainly the paucity of true believers for this point. If I did verily beleeve that Chriſt were riſen from the dead, and <hi>all power now given him in Heaven and in earth;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 28.18.</note> would I ſo ſlovenly ſerve him as I do? my ſervice to him is ſuch as if he were rotting in the grave, and not ſitting at the right hand of the Father; why do I therefore Cozen my ſelfe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114709:16"/>and others with a vaine conceit that I beleeve the Reſurrection?</p>
            <p>Laſtly, let me tell you, that if we do in ſome meaſure believe Chriſts Reſurrection, yet the more eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and arguments to ſhow it, the ſweeter and ſtronger growes our faith. The things indeed to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved cannot be demonſtrated by reaſon; but yet this may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated by reaſon, that it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry reaſonable to beleeve them, or (to ſpeake with S. <hi>Aug.</hi>) that they may be demonſtrated by reaſon:<note place="margin">1. Quòd non ſit ſtultum ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia credere; deinde quòd ſit ſtultum ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia non credere.</note> firſt, that it is not a fooliſh thing to beleeve thoſe things; and further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more that it is a fooliſh thing not to beleeve them. The more evidences and arguments therefore to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the too too reaſonablenes of Chriſts Reſurrection, the ſweeter and ſtronger growes our faith; <hi>Foraſmuch as many have taken in hand,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 1.1.</note> &amp;c. <hi>that thou mighteſt know the certainty of thoſe things wherein thou haſt been inſtructed;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Though at my firſt Catechizing in the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Religion, I ſhould ſimply
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114709:17"/>beleeve the Articles of faith; yet to know the certainty of them much eſtabliſheth my faith. Hereunto tends that;<note place="margin">Rom. 1.11.</note> 
               <hi>for I long to ſee you, that I may impart unto you ſome ſpiritual gift, to the end you may be eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed; and night and day praying ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly that wee might ſee your face and might perfect that which is lacking in your faith;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 3.</note> namely by further doctrine and proofe of the Goſpel, more and more evidence the truth of it unto you. That therefore the Chriſtian may know the certainty of this thing wherein he hath been Catechized, namely Chriſts Reſurrection from the dead; the third day he roſe again from the dead, theſe things may ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently do it;</p>
            <p>Firſt, the <hi>prediction</hi> or teſtimony of the Old Teſtament.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the teſtimony of ſo many eye witneſſes, eſpecially the Grand-Jury of the Apoſtles to whom he often appeared in the fleſh after the Reſurrection.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the teſtimony of the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114709:17"/>ſpirit, which after his Reſurrection and Aſcenſion Chriſt ſent down a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his Apoſtles and Diſciples to give them extraordinary holines of life, extraordinary power to work miracles, extraordinary boldnes and zeale to preach the Goſpel, extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary ſucceſſe in preaching it; theſe things could not be done by one that was in the power and hands of death, but by one that was ſet down at the power and right hand of the Father.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> And firſt the prediction of the Old Teſtament is a good argument to the Chriſtian to beleeve Chriſts Reſurrection,<note place="margin">Codicem portat Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeus undo credat Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, libra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rii noſtri facti ſunt quomodo ſolent ſervi poſt domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos codices ferre, ut illi portando deficiant; illi legendo proficiant. (Aug. Pſ. 56.)</note> becauſe he ſees he is taught to beleeve no new thing, but that onely which hath been ſo often, and ſo long agoe foretold by thoſe Scriptures which the very Jew, the maine enemy to the Reſurrection cannot deny, nay zealouſly main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines. The Jews carry the bookes, by which the Chriſtians may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve; they are become our book-carriers; even as ſervants carry their maſters bookes after them, that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:114709:18"/>whereas the one are weary with carrying, the other may profit by reading.</p>
            <p>But where are theſe predictions of the Old Teſtament? ſurely had we all thoſe places which our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour alledged to the two Diſciples, <hi>beginning at Moſes and all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 24.37.</note> 
               <hi>and expounding to them in all the Scriptures the things that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned his paſſion, and his glory,</hi> we ſhould be marvellouſly furniſhed: or had we thoſe which it's likely <hi>S. Peter</hi> uſed in his Sermon:<note place="margin">Act. 3.24.</note> 
               <hi>All the Prophets from Samuel and thoſe that follow after, as many as have ſpoken have likewiſe foretold of theſe dayes;</hi> or thoſe by which <hi>Apollo</hi> ſo mightily convinced the Jews,<note place="margin">Act. 19.</note> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the Scriptures that Jeſus was Chriſt:<note place="margin">Act. 28.23</note> and thoſe whereby <hi>Paul</hi> continued perſwading the Jews con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Jeſus, from morning till evening, both out of Moſes and the Prophets;</hi> we ſhould be richly fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, underſtood we all theſe; But howſoever let theſe expreſs pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces prove the Reſurrection;</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:114709:18"/>
            <p>Firſt, that of the ſixteenth <hi>Pſalm,</hi> urged by St. Peter Act. 2. <hi>My fleſh ſhall reſt in hope, becauſe thou wilt not leave my Soul in Hell, nor ſuffer thy holy one to ſee corruption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, that of the ſecond Pſalm, urged by S. Paul Act. 13. <hi>Thou art my Son, this day have I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten thee;</hi> manifeſtly declared thee to be my very ſon now by my raiſing thee from the dead.<note place="margin">Rom. 1.4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, that of Eſay 52.14, 15. <hi>As many were aſtonied at thee,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſo ſhall he ſprinkle many nations; the Kings ſhall ſhut their mouths at him, for that which hath not been told them ſhall they ſee,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And that of Eſay 53.10. <hi>When thou ſhalt make his Soul an offering for ſin, he ſhall ſee his ſeed, he ſhall prolong his dayes,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, not to name more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, all thoſe places prove this, that ſhow he muſt conquer death: for how ſhould he conquer death for others, that were deteined by it himſelf?<note place="margin">Eſay 25.7.</note> 
               <hi>he wil deſtroy in this moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the face of the covering caſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114709:19"/>over all people, and the vail that is ſpread over all nations;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 13.14.</note> 
               <hi>And I will ranſom them from the power of the grave.</hi> Fiftly, all thoſe places that ſpeak of his everlaſting Kingdome; <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto us a child is borne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 9.7.</note> 
               <hi>and the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ſhall be upon his ſhoulders; of the increaſe of his government and peace there ſhall be no end,</hi> &amp;c. theſe and many other the like places may aſſure us againſt Jew or Gentile, that for the Reſurrection or any other myſtery about the Saviour of the world, we believe no new thing, but that onely which often and long agoe hath been foretold by thoſe Scriptures that were highly magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, not onely by the Jew, but alſo by the Gentile; when <hi>Ptolomy</hi> that famous King of <hi>Egypt</hi> cauſed them a long time before our Saviors com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the fleſh to be tranſlated out of hebrew into greek, a tongue more known to the nations, that thoſe Holy Scriptures alſo might be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter known to the nations: our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and ſtay of faith therefore may be, that with S. <hi>Paul</hi> we ſay and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:114709:19"/>none other things then thoſe which the Prophets and Moſes-did ſay ſhould come,<note place="margin">Act. 26.23.</note> 
               <hi>that Chriſt ſhould ſuffer, and that he ſhould be the firſt that ſhould riſe from the dead<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> Secondly, the teſtimony of ſo many eye-witneſſes witneſſing the truth of his Reſurrection from his often apparitions unto them, as Firſt, to <hi>Mary Magdalene:</hi> 2. to the women by the way going from the ſepulcher to the Diſciples, to acquaint them with that which had befalne there: 3. to Peter alone: 4. to the two Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples travelling to <hi>Emaus,</hi> whoſe eyes were a while holden that they knew him not; 5. to the Diſciples gathered together, and the doores ſhut upon them when <hi>Thomas</hi> was away, and all theſe five apparitions were the firſt day. 6. to the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples eight dayes after, when <hi>Thomas</hi> alſo was among them; 7. to ſeven of the Diſciples at the Sea of <hi>Tibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rias,</hi> when they had that extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary draught of fiſhes, at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand bidding then caſt on the right hand, though all night they had
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:114709:20"/>fiſhed, and catched nothing. 8. In a mountaine of <hi>Galilee</hi> as himſelf being alive had foretold them; and this moſt thinke to be that famous apparition underſtood here by <hi>S. Paul,</hi> when he tells us of one of his appearings to be to more then 500 brethren at once. 9 Upon Mount <hi>Olivet,</hi> from whence he aſcended up to Heaven; And theſe appariti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are recorded in the Goſpels; whereunto <hi>S. Paul</hi> mentioning ſome of theſe, adds alſo ſome other apparitions beſides; as this of his appearing to more then 500 bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren at once, if it be not the ſame with that apparition in <hi>Galilee;</hi> alſo a diſtinct apparition to <hi>James,</hi> alſo another diſtinct one when he ſaies, To all the Apoſtles; and laſtly an apparition to himſelf, as one borne out of time: and theſe are the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes choſen before of God (as Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſpeaks) <hi>to whom he ſhewed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf openly;</hi> he ſhewed himſelf open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>not to all the people, but to witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes choſen before of God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 10.</note> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeeing wee are compaſſed about
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:114709:20"/>with ſuch a cloud of witneſſes, we have ground ſure enough for our faith. Nothing can be objected againſt their teſtimony, but that either they were deceivers, or were deceived; Deceivers, ſo the Jews objected, that while the watch ſlept his Diſciples came by night, and ſtole his body away, and ſo ſpread abroad the errour of his Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, <hi>Matt.</hi> 28.13. but this is too too incredible; it is too too incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible that they could do this, and it is more then too too incredible that they would do it. Firſt, too incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that they could do it, for conſider a text in St. <hi>Matt.</hi> 27.62. &amp;c. <hi>Now the next day that followed the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The High Prieſts ſaid to Pilate, command therefore that the ſepulchre be made ſure,</hi> &amp;c. If they had intended to ſteale away his body, why not the firſt-night before the Watch was ſet? for all the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances here well conſidered, give it a thing too too incredible, that they could do it after ſo vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, diligent, and abundant Watch,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:114709:21"/>that queſtionleſs was ſet, for why? they came about it even on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day, and that was an high day too. Secondly, the very words that our Saviour ſaid, that within 3 dayes he would riſe again, ſtuck in their ſtomacks vilely; 3. They confeſſed that if it ſhould ſo fall out, the laſt errour would be worſe then the firſt. 4. they had full leave of <hi>Pilate</hi> to do whatſoever they would for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king all ſure, would they not thinke you therefore ſet a moſt vigilant Watch, &amp;c? and ſo it appears they did,<note place="margin">Matt. 27.66.</note> 
               <hi>They went and made the ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre ſure,</hi> &amp;c. they would not truſt any other; how ſhould it therefore be a thing credible, that theſe ſhould or durſt be ſo negligent as to fall a ſleep, nay would be ſo negligent, for in all likelyhood in a thing that they had ſuch ſpeciall care of, they pickt out for the Watch ſome forward zealots, that the very zeale of the cauſe would keepe them waking, as well as the aw and dread of authority; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially it being but one night they
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:114709:21"/>watched; how is it credible alſo that the poor ſneaks, the Diſciples, that ſhewed their heels ſo finely when their maſter was apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſhould now when he was in the grave, take heart of grace ſo coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geouſly, to attempt the thing againſt ſo ſtrong a Watch? how further is it credible, that the rowing away of the ſtone before the door of the ſepulchre, the ſtone that was a very great one, when the women that came to anoint him tooke great care how to get it rowled away; how credible that this ſhould not have waked ſome of the Watch hard by? how further is it credible, if the Diſciples had ſtolne him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, that the winding ſheet ſhould have been left behind in the ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre, lying decently in one place, and the napkin that was about his head wrapped up in another place by it ſelf; would they not rather, if they had ſtolne him, not have ſtript him but carried him away as he was in his grave-geare? common humanity would not let them ſtrip
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:114709:22"/>him, and carry him away in ſo hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid a manner as ſtark naked; and common wit would not let them thinke, that they ſhould have had ſo much leiſure without feare of waking any of the Watch, as to ſtrip him, eſpecially being wound up in linnen cloaths, with Mirrhe and other ſpices of a clammy and ſtick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nature like pitch; to ſtrip him of this, and to have leiſure then to wrap up the linnen cloaths, and the napkin upon his head ſeverally by themſelves, theſe are not ſignes of ſuch as are in feare and haſt, ſo that it is no marvell that hereat the Evangeliſt ſaid,<note place="margin">John 20.8.</note> that <hi>the Diſciple ſaw and believed.</hi> How (laſtly) is it credible, that the Watch durſt go home to the high Prieſts with ſuch a fine tale in their mouths? <hi>While we ſlept, his Diſciples came by night and ſtole him away;</hi> what had this been but to have pronounced ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence againſt their own Souls? when the Angel had brought <hi>Peter</hi> miraculouſly out of priſon,<note place="margin">Act. 12.19.</note> the keepers were examined, and put to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:114709:22"/>death, though innocently, for the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape, what could they have looked for but the like ſauce? the impunity of the Watch is argument enough to any that hath but halfe an eye in his head, that there was dawbing in the matter, and caſting heads about it: and laſtly, that Dilemma of <hi>Aug.</hi> againſt this fine tale of the Watch. Either it was falſe that they ſlept,<note place="margin">Aut falſum erat quòd dormie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, &amp; mendaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus credere non debue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt; aut verum erat quòd dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mierant, &amp; quod fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum eſt neſcierunt. in Pſ. 55. Stulta in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſania! ſi vigilabas, quare per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſiſti? ſi dormiebas, unde ſciſti? in Pſ. 36.</note> and ſo lyars are not to be believed; or it was true, and then how could they tell what hapned? fooliſh madnes! if thou waſt awake, why didſt thou ſuffer it? if thou waſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep, how didſt thou know it?</p>
            <p>Secondly, it is more then too in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible they would do it: would they that being Jews knew well what God and Religion meant, have dared to have father'd ſuch a groſſe forgery on God? it is the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, one of them, which our Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle here inſtanceth in; If Chriſt be not riſen, then are we found falſe witneſſes of God, which ſome might thinke, (irreligious and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane wretches that they are) to be
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:114709:23"/>no ſuch great argument, yet weigh it well in theſe perſons the Apoſtles, and a forcinger argument cannot be brought; for how canſt thou ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, that the Apoſtles, who being no ſuch fooles, as appears well enough by putting the wiſe Jews ſo to it to call councell upon coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell againſt them, would of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, without Divine warrant, have attempted ſo fooliſh a thing as the preaching of obedience up and down the world to a crucified man, no otherwiſe riſen from the dead then by ſtealing his body out of the grave? what hope could ever they have of any ſucceſſe? No hope from him whom they preached, whoſe own conſciences told them he was yet in the power of death; no hope from God whom they ſo foul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly belyed, no hope from any thing in themſelves, not from eloquence and excellency of ſpeech to perſwade, they were but rude and illiterate men; not from wealth and riches to corrupt, ſhoos on their feet and a ſtaff in their hand was moſt of that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:114709:23"/>they had; not from authority and greatnes to awe and prejudice, they were but contemptible fiſhermen &amp; the like; not from number and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude to overrun and ſubdue, they were but eleven ſilly ſneaks, that had all run away when their Maſter was apprehended, no hope therefore from any thing in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: no hope further from any docibleneſs and inclinablineſs of the parties to be perſwaded, not any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clineableneſs of the Jew; Not him but Barrabas, and Crucify him, Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cify him was the loud and joynt cry of the Jew; the Jew was hardned therefore againſt any ſuch Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; it had been as eaſie for theſe fiſher men, the Apoſtles, to have ſpoken to the fiſhes of the Sea, to have made them follow them on the dry land, as to have ſpoken to the people of the Jews to have made them follow them in the Doctrine and beliefe of Chriſts Reſurrection upon their own bare word; they that cared not for all Chriſts miracles when he was
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:114709:24"/>alive, but Crucified him, were they likely to have believed the bare aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertions of fiſhermen for his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection? Not any inclinableneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in the Gentile,<note place="margin">Act. 17.32.</note> it was that <hi>they mocked at when they heard of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection;</hi> it was that that <hi>Paul</hi> was glad to qualify with this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of inſinuation in the beginning when he was to ſpeake of it to the Gentile;<note place="margin">Act. 26.8.</note> 
               <hi>Why ſhould it be thought a thing incredible with you, that God ſhould raiſe the dead?</hi> be it a thing never ſo hard, why ſhould it be thought above Gods ability to do? It was that alſo that when <hi>Paul</hi> was in the earneſtneſs of his ſpeech about the aſſertion of it,<note place="margin">Act. 26.24.</note> 
               <hi>made Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus break out with a loud voice and ſay; Paul thou art beſide thy ſelfe;</hi> was the Gentile therefore likely to be inclinable to this Doctrine, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially Chriſts ſuffering being pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, and all ſeeing it, and his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection being private and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, and but a few ſuppoſed wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of it? and thoſe few oppoſed almoſt by all that nation, the nation
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:114709:24"/>of the Jews, that if there had been any ſuch thing ſhould have brought the knowledge thereof unto the Gentiles, would they therefore that were no ſtark fooles, have gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a thing of ſo great folly, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they had no hope of ſucceſſe from him that they preached, as not ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen; no hope from God, as belyed by them; no hope from any thing in themſelves, as being without elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, without riches, without au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, without multitude; no hope from any inclinableneſs in the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to be perſwaded Jew or Gentile, as being utter enemies the one to the mention of the name of <hi>Jeſus of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zereth,</hi> the other to the mention of the Reſurrection. Either therefore they were very Idiots and ſtark fooles, and why then were the wiſeſt Jews ſo put to it by them, to lay heads together, and to aſſemble councel after councel? or elſe they were wiſe enough; and why then ſhould any thinke they would at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt ſuch a fooliſh thing without good ground and reaſon?</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe they had been ſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeene as not to have conſidered
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:114709:25"/>theſe things at firſt, yet would they not when the ſtorme once begun to fall on them, and the world riſe up in armes againſt them, ſeeing the impoſſibility every way of making their Legend, their lying Legend take: would they not then have deſiſted? would not fair nor foul means have made one of them at leaſt, at laſt have bewrayed the whole buſines? but that all their life long, in ſpite of what the world could do, they ſhould continue eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of them in moſt conſtant aſſeveration of the Reſurrection; certainly had they been nothing but deceivers, it is not imaginable that the world could have a pack of ſuch, except they had been very incarnate Devils: but their writings and much more their lives ſhewed them to have been rather incarnate Angels. Again if they would have done this they ſhould either have taken our Saviour for an impoſtor, deceiving them of his promiſe, that he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed them he would riſe again the third day, and ſo they ſhould rather
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:114709:25"/>have hated him as an Impoſtor, then preached, him as Saviour; or elſe ſhould have taken him as the true Saviour indeed, though yet deteined in the grave, and ſo they would never have gone about to have preached him that was Truth; by meere lyes and falſhood; they could not thinke that the true Saviour would thinke well of falſe Apoſtles; and therefore it is too in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible they could, it is more then too too incredible they would preach the Reſurrection as Meere Deceivers.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Not as deceived with any fantaſme or apparition Diaboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call;</p>
            <p>For firſt, They were ſure the body was not in the ſepulchre, their own ſenſe and the ſenſe of all the Jews viewing the empty ſepulchre, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed them of that.</p>
            <p>Secondly, They were ſure none had privately ſtollen the body away and laid it elſewhere, becauſe of the Watch that kept the ſepulchre, and becauſe of the grave-cloaths left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:114709:26"/>and the napkin that was u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon his head wrapt up alone: none would have carried away a dead Ghaſtly body, and that ſo full of wounds and gored blood and Ghaſtly viſaged (for the Napkin of his head alſo was taken off) none would have carried away a dead body in ſuch an horrid manner.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, They had a Viſion of Angels that affirmed unto the women that he was riſen, and withall remembred them that it was but as he had told them before, that he would riſe again the third day, and therefore they need not diſtruſt it.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, They had (after) many corporall apparitions unto them of our Saviour himſelf; and ſtill you may obſerve there goes alwayes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, with the apparition, ſome no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table circumſtance, one or other, to be an argument to confirme the verity of it, as:</p>
            <p>Firſt, for the apparition to <hi>Mary,</hi> you have this obſervable circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, that though Jeſus had talked
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:114709:26"/>with her a while, and ſhe knew him not, but thought he had been the Gardiner, yet at the ſpeaking of one bare word <hi>(Mary)</hi> ſhe preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knew him, and ſayes <hi>Rabboni:</hi> this was either a plaine effect of his Divinity, ſo on the ſudden to work on her heart; or elſe of his huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to ſpeake juſt in that familiar form which he uſed when he was alive, ſo that ſhe knew him to be he by his voice; The Divil may ſooner counterfeit a viſage then a voice.</p>
            <p>Again, for the apparition to the two Diſciples by the way, you have theſe two circumſtances,
<list>
                  <item>Firſt, Their hearts extraordinarily burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing within them while he opened to them the Scriptures, which argues his Divinity.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, A ſpeciall manifeſtation of himſelfe unto them by breaking of bread, uſing the ſame form of thankſ-giving, or ſame form of action in breaking, or both, which he uſed while he was alive, and that argued the ſame humanity.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:114709:27"/>
            <p>Again, for the apparition to the Apoſtles when <hi>Thomas</hi> was abſent, you have two circumſtances that are moſt demonſtrative of a true living body. Firſt this, <hi>handle me, and ſee me, for a ſpirit has not fleſh and bones as you ſee me have:</hi> Then this;<note place="margin">Luke 24.41.</note> 
               <hi>Have ye here any meat,</hi> &amp;c? Though the Divell can form a body of the Elements, a body that may be felt, yet not true live body, that can eat and digeſt meat, not a true live body that hath fleſh and bones, that hath heat and pulſe, and all the temper of a true live body; If this were ſo, how ſhould we be ſure one of another, that we are not fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſms? Nay, if handle mee, and ſee me, were not a good argument, how were the Jews ſure that it was the true <hi>Jeſus</hi> that was Crucified, the true <hi>Jeſus</hi> that was laid in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulcher? If they were ſure they Crucified and buryed the true <hi>Jeſus,</hi> the Diſciples were as ſure that it was the true <hi>Jeſus</hi> that roſe again, and appeared unto them. And this is that circumſtance which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:114709:27"/>brought <hi>Thomas</hi> off from his infidelity, when <hi>eight dayes after Chriſt appeared unto them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 20.28.</note> 
               <hi>Thomas being with them, and thruſt his hand into his ſide, and ſaid, my Lord and my God.</hi> And this is ſo ſtrong an argument that S. <hi>Peter</hi> cares for no more, Act. 10.41. <hi>He ſhewed himſelf openly not to all the people, but to choſen witneſſes, even to us, who did eat and drinke with him after he roſe from the dead:</hi> he did eat and drinke with them moſt familiarly, and ſenſibly converſed with them; even as familiarly, and ſenſibly as when he was alive; ſo that if we were ſure of him then, we are as ſure of him now. And this is the argument S. <hi>John</hi> beats ſo on, <hi>That which we have heard, which we have ſeene with our eyes,</hi> &amp;c. 1 John. 1.1. Conſider now further, that this was forty dayes together that he thus at ſeverall times converſed with them, that all his ſpeech at thoſe times with them was not about ſuch things as the ſpeech of a deceiving Divell would have been, <hi>but of the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:114709:28"/>things pertaining to the Kingdome of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 1.3.</note> of the things whereby the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles afterwards deſtroyed every where the Kingdome of the Divels, and their Idolatrous worſhip. Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der alſo that the Diſciples were ſo incredulous formerly of the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, that the words of the women that told them he was riſen, ſeemed to them <hi>idle tales;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 24.11. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that alſo our Saviour upbraided them with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beliefe and hardneſs of heart, that they believed not them, (namely the women and the two Diſciples and <hi>Peter</hi>) which had ſeene him af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he was riſen; That <hi>Thomas</hi> alſo; for all that the other Diſciples aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it unto him, yet he would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve none of them all, hee would believe nothing but his own hands and fingers; would theſe men there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that were ſo hard of beliefe, would ever they have believed ſuch a thing, without moſt infallible proofes? as it is, Act. 1.3. <hi>To whom he ſhould himſelf alive after his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, by moſt infallible proofes,</hi> &amp;c. and therefore neither were they
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:114709:28"/>deceived, but knew well enough what they ſaid, when they anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the High Prieſts, and rulers of the Jews (ſtraightly charging them, to ſpeake no more of <hi>Jeſus</hi> and the Reſurrection) with a <hi>Non poſſumus, wee cannot but ſpeak the things which wee have ſeene, and hoard,</hi> Act. 4. 20. If therefore they could neither bee deceived, nor deceivers, there is weight enough in thoſe words; <hi>this Jeſus hath God raiſed up; whereof wee are all witneſſes;</hi> and again they urge it, Act. 2.32. Act. 3. Act. 5. Act. 10. The teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny therefore of theſe <hi>eye-witneſſes,</hi> is in the ſecond place aſſurance e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough unto us of Chriſts Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the teſtimony of the <hi>Spirit</hi> which Chriſt after his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and aſcenſion ſent down from Heaven, to be a powerfull witneſſe unto the world of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection; by giving unto his, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary grace of holineſs, extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary grace of preaching the Goſpel, extraordinary grace of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:114709:29"/>confirming it by miracles, extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary grace of a happy ſucceſſe in the buſines, to draw in ſo ſhort a time almoſt the world after them; theſe things ſhew that Chriſt was not in the power and hands of death, but ſate down at the power and right hand of his Father. It is plaine, a King is not in hold by his enemies, when every where he does ſuch things that makes the world ring of him; as plain that Chriſt was not deteined in hold by that enemy death, when every where by the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> which he ſent, he did ſuch things as made the whole world ring of him.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> Whence (firſt) had the Apoſtles and Apoſtolicall men that extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary grace of preaching the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, but onely from fulfilling that promiſe in Act. 1.8? <hi>ye ſhall receive power after that the Holy Ghoſt is come upon you, and ye ſhall be wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes unto me both in Jeruſalem,</hi> &amp;c. Hence had they their extraordinary grace of promptneſs, grace of dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:114709:29"/>grace of ſincerity, grace of patience, grace of tendereſt love and affection after the Salvation (if they could) of every Soul.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The grace of <hi>boldneſs,</hi> whence could they have it, but from that power of the Holy Ghoſt coming upon them? How timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and white liver'd otherwiſe they were, their running all away when their Maſter was apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, their hardieſt mans, I meane, <hi>Peters</hi> denyall of him at the ſpeech of a ſilly maid, their lurkings and underhand meetings, both before and a while after the Reſurrection, meeting but onely, for feare of the Jews, in private places, and in the night, and with the doores ſhut upon them; theſe ſhow how timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous otherwiſe they were. What transformed them therefore from ſuch hares and harts, into ſuch ſtout Lions as afterwards they ſhowed themſelves, but onely this power of the Holy Ghoſt coming on them? This made them, that before ran away and hid their heads in corners,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:114709:30"/>to be bold afterwards, to preach <hi>Jeſus of Nazereth</hi> to all the people, to all the prieſts and rulers, to all comers that would hear them; <hi>in the publick Temple,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 5.42.</note> 
               <hi>teaching and preaching Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> See what difference there is between their former fearfulneſs, and their then boldneſs. Act. 2.14. <hi>But Peter ſtanding up with the eleven lift up his voice,</hi> &amp;c. all things make pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely for expreſſing their ſtoutneſs and boldnes; The ſtanding up, the lifting up the voice, the forme of words themſelves, <hi>Yee men of Judaea;</hi> &amp;c. words of meer au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, words for emperours to ſpeake, ſo verſe 22. <hi>ye men of Iſrael,</hi> &amp;c. and 36. <hi>Therefore let all the houſe of Iſrael know aſſuredly;</hi> See here their <hi>boldneſs,</hi> and their former timorouſneſs, and none would take them for the ſame men, at moſt but other men in the ſame skins. Ay but this is but a flaſh before the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, before that the rulers have medled with them; dare they be ſo bold alſo before them? See whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:114709:30"/>they dare or no. Chap. 4. v. 5. They are apprehended, kept in hold a night, convented the next day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore an aſſembly that might have ſtruck terrour into them; <hi>And it came to paſſe on the morrow, that their Rulers and elders,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>were gathered together;</hi> Here was greatneſs enough to have daſhed them, but what ſayes the Story? <hi>But Peter filled with the Holy Ghoſt:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 4.8.</note> Not without good cauſe is this preface, otherwiſe ſuch great looks had been enough to have daunted ſuch two poore ſneakes; <hi>But Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter filled with the holy Ghoſt, ſaid,</hi> &amp;c. Words of ſuch ſtoutneſs and bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that thoſe great ones wondered ſuch ſneakes ſhould be ſo bold: <hi>When they ſaw the boldneſs of Peter and John they marvelled;</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſe 13.</note> boldneſs to ſay, <hi>Bee it known unto you all,</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſ. 10, 11.</note> &amp;c. <hi>whom yee Crucified,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſet at nought by you builders,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> Ay but this was the firſt time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they had taſted of the whip, they had nothing but threats, and great words given them there;
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:114709:31"/>durſt they do ſo the ſecond time, and after they had ſmarted?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> That the ſecond and third time too they durſt do ſo, you have it Chap. 5.17. and 29. and alſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they had ſmarted, being well beaten with rods, you have it verſe 42. <hi>dayly in the Temple, and in every houſe they ceaſed not to teach and preach Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Grace of <hi>promptneſs of ſpeech,</hi> whence had they it, but from this power of the Holy Ghoſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon them? it could be nothing but this that looſed the tongue of thoſe ſtammerers, that made thoſe liſpers ſpeake ſo plaine, that made thoſe poor fiſhermen, (as mute otherwiſe almoſt as the fiſh they caught) to become on the ſudden the worlds oratours, to extemporize before aſſemblies and congregations upon every occaſion, to argue with Jew and Gentile, with Phariſee and Philoſopher, and ſo to argue as their adverſaries were driven to anſwer, as <hi>Stevens</hi> did him, to leave reaſoning and go to ſuborning.<note place="margin">Act. 6.9.11.</note> Then <hi>there
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:114709:31"/>aroſe certaine of the Synagogue,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and they ſuborned men,</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">Act. 9.29.</note> Or as <hi>Pauls</hi> him, <hi>He ſpake boldly in the name of the Lord Jeſus, and diſputed againſt the Graecians, but they went about to ſlay him.</hi> Whence could theſe mute fiſhermen have had this promptneſs, and preſentneſs, yea and wiſdom of ſpeech; but onely from the power of the Holy Ghoſt coming on them?<note place="margin">Pſ. 8.2.</note> 
               <hi>But out of the mouth of Bades and ſucklings haſt thou perfected praiſe.</hi> And <hi>I will give you a mouth, and wiſdome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 21.15.</note> 
               <hi>which all your adverſaries ſhall not be able to gainſay, nor reſiſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job. 12.20.</note> Theſe let you ſee what did the deed; <hi>He removeth away the ſpeech of the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty,</hi> &amp;c. ſo he giveth ſometime the ſpeech to the ſtammerer;<note place="margin">Job. 32.8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>but there is a ſpirit in man, and the inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Almighty giveth them underſtanding.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 4.13. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Now when they ſaw the boldneſs of Peter and John,</hi> &amp;c. It was ſtrange, that they ſhould ſpeake ſo roundly, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundly,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> of whom it could not have been expected, as being unlearned
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:114709:32"/>and ignorant men, that they could have gone on above five words toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, without hacks and hawes about matters ſo out of their element.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Grace of <hi>extraordinary diligence,</hi> whence had they it; but from this power of the Holy Ghoſt? if you conſider that they had nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther profit to draw them on to take that pains; <hi>for ſilver and gold have I none,</hi> (not ſo much as to give a beggar his almes) ſaid he that was the chiefe of them; And <hi>theſe hands have miniſtred to my neceſſity,</hi> ſaid he that was not his inferior; no profit therefore to draw them on. No <hi>honour</hi> neither; for they were therefore counted <hi>the filth of the world, and the offscowring of all things;</hi> If you conſider alſo, that their breeding was a private coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey-breeding, and a quiet retried life, led upon lakes and rivers, not made to be the worlds poſts, to trudge from City to City, from na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to nation, from people to peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, from Kingdome to Kingdome, and there ſtill to have no reſt to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:114709:32"/>their fleſh,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 7.</note> 
               <hi>but be troubled on every ſide, fightings without, fears within;</hi> beſides their aſſiduity in preaching, in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, private<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and publickly; If you conſider withall, how well their ſucceſſors now a dayes love their eaſe, when they need not trudge up and down the world as they did to preach the Goſpel; it were well if they would but reſide at their own cures and take a little pains there; If you conſider all theſe, whence can you ſay they had this <hi>extraordinary dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence,</hi> but from the power of the Holy Ghoſt? it could be nothing but this, that made them ſo dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, that the rulers of the Jews could ſay of them in a ſhort time; <hi>Behold you have filled Jeruſalem with your doctrine:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 5.28.</note> ſo diligent, that as it is in the ſame Chapter, <hi>dayly in the Temple and from houſe to houſe they ceaſed not to teach and preach Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> ſo diligent, that <hi>Peter</hi> is made as is were an Ubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitary, <hi>As Peter paſſed thorowout all quarters,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 9.32.</note> &amp;c. ſo diligent, that
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:114709:33"/>
               <hi>Demetrius</hi> could ſay of one of them, namely <hi>Paul, Sirs, ye ſee and heare, that not alone at Epheſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 19.26.</note> 
               <hi>but almoſt thorowout all Aſia this Paul hath perſwaded and turned away much people;</hi> ſo diligent, that other ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of theirs could ſay when they came to <hi>Theſſulonica, Theſe that have turned the world up ſide down are come hither alſo;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 17.6.</note> ſo diligent, that by their means in a ſmall time, <hi>the ſound of the Goſpel went into all the earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10.18.</note> 
               <hi>and their words unto the end of the world;</hi> and that leaven of the Kingdome ſpoken of Mat. 13. <hi>had leavened the whole lumpe;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, Grace of <hi>ſincerity,</hi> to take all this pains for no ſiniſter worldly reſpect whatſoever, but meerly for the Goſpels ſake, to plant it; whence could they have this ſincerity, but from the ſame power of the Holy Ghoſt? How ſincerely they preached the Goſpel without ſeeking either praiſe or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit by it, ſee a little;</p>
            <p>Not <hi>praiſe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 3.12.</note> for when upon the cure of the lame man, the people came
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:114709:33"/>flocking about them and admiring them almoſt as halfe Gods, what ſayes S. <hi>Peter? Ye men of Iſrael, why looke ye ſo earneſtly on us, as if by our own power or holineſs, we had made this man to walke?</hi> And when upon the like occaſion the men of <hi>Lyſtra</hi> would have honoured <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> for Gods, they were ſo far from ſeeking their own praiſe, that they did all they could to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it,<note place="margin">Act. 14.14. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>they ran in among the people, crying out and ſaying, Sirs, why do you theſe things? we alſo are men of like paſſions with you,</hi> &amp;c. And when ſome magnifying <hi>Paul,</hi> and ſome <hi>Apollo,</hi> and ſome <hi>Cephas,</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling themſelves after their great Maſters, <hi>I am of Paul,</hi> &amp;c. how doth <hi>Paul</hi> take up all pride that might ariſe thereupon?<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>who is Paul, and who is Apollo, but miniſters by whom ye believed?</hi> And <hi>we preach. not our ſelves,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.5.</note> 
               <hi>but Chriſt Jeſus the Lord, and our ſelves your ſervants for Chriſts ſuke.</hi> If therefore that of our Saviours be true,<note place="margin">John 7.18.</note> 
               <hi>He that ſpeaketh of himſelfe, ſeeketh his own
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:114709:34"/>glory; but he that ſeeketh his glory that ſent him, the ſame is true, and no unrighteouſneſs is in him;</hi> then they ſeeking not their own glory, when it was offered them, but anothers that ſent them, it muſt needs be that they ſpeake not of themſelves, but acted by his ſpirit that ſent them.</p>
            <p>So for <hi>profit,</hi> how ſincerely they preached the Goſpel without per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe aime that way? Their hungry bellyes, oftentimes <hi>in hunger and thirſt,</hi> (which was not voluntary ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence, for that is meant after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, <hi>in faſtings often;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 11.27.</note>) Their cold backs, <hi>in cold and nakedneſs;</hi> Their purſe pennileſs,<note place="margin">Act. 3.6.</note> 
               <hi>ſilver and gold have I none:</hi> theſe ſhow what a little gain they made of the Goſpel. <hi>Paul</hi> would never have writ for a cloake as far as from Rome to Troas, four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred miles, if, poor man, he had had that variety, or his converts had been ſo franke unto him, as to have furniſhed him with money to have bought a new one; he made but a little harveſt of the Goſpel, that was glad to write for an old cloake 400
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:114709:34"/>miles to hap him againſt winter. <hi>The cloak that I left at Troas with Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.13.</note> 
               <hi>bring with thee.</hi> And that it was for happing to his back againſt the cold winter, you may gather from that which followeth; <hi>do thy dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to come before winter;</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſe 21.</note> verily this argument if any other, that the Appoſtles ſhould with that <hi>ſincerity</hi> preach the Goſpel, all <hi>praiſe</hi> and all <hi>profit</hi> ſet aſide, this helps to confirme the truth of the Goſpel, if any other, that they ſhould take ſuch infinite pains in that harveſt <hi>(ſend forth La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers into thine harveſt)</hi> and aime at no harveſt at all thereby for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the world.<note place="margin">Mat. 9.38.</note> And therefore not without good reaſon does St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſo often ſtand upon this thing,<note place="margin">Act. 20.33 1 Cor. 4.11. and 9.3. 2 Cor. 11.10. and 12.14. 1 Theſ. 2.5.</note> to ſtabliſh his converts in the truth of the Goſpel which he preached, <hi>Neither at any time uſed we flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring words:</hi> Who is there even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, that would ſhut the door for nought? But what a deal of pains tooke they for nought? or rather they knew well enough whom they truſted, and who it was that ſaid,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:114709:35"/>
               <hi>lift up your eyes and looke on the fields, for they are white already to harveſt, He that reapeth, recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth wages.</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 4.36</note> They would never have ſweat ſo in this harveſt and ſo little wages here, but that they knew of thoſe other wages.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, The grace of <hi>extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary patience,</hi> whence alſo could they have it, but from the power of the Holy Ghoſt? who were they, and what were their bodyes? was their ſtrength the ſtrength of ſtones, and their fleſh of braſſe,<note place="margin">Job. 6.12.</note> that they ſhould be able to hold out againſt hunger and thirſt, againſt cold and nakedneſs, ſtripes and impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, &amp;c? was their Souls not like other mens, but heavenly ſpirits ſheathed in earthly bodyes, that they ſhould not be overcome; no not much affected with all the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probries, reproaches, ignominies that the world could caſt upon them; that all the paine, and all the ſhame the world could put them to, they ſhould ſtill continue as ſtrong, as ſteddy as anvills unſtirred,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:114709:35"/>unmoved for all the blows? What can this be but the power of the Holy Ghoſt coming upon them? if ſo many ſtrong men with Iron hammers ſhould let drive at a piece of glaſs, or earthen veſſel, and not be able to breake it, all men would ſay, it were an enchanted glaſs or veſſel; how many let drive at thoſe earthen veſſels, the humane natures of the Apoſtles, with ſuch bats and blows as would almoſt have broken ſteele and adamant? That therefore theſe earthen veſſels were not broken with all theſe blows, what ſhould be the reaſon, but onely that they were enchanted, enchanted with that power of the Holy Ghoſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon them, that made their frail natures hold out ſo againſt dint of ſtroke of all perſecutions? <hi>I will turn aſide</hi> (ſaith Moſes) <hi>and ſee this great ſight, why the buſh burnes with fire and conſumeth not;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exo. 3.3.</note> that was a ſtrange thing to his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit; ſo a ſtrange thing it muſt needs be to any ones conſideration, that the Apoſtles, who for their fraile
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:114709:36"/>humane natures were nothing but buſhes, and bruſhwood, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtibleſt ſtuffe that could be, ſtrange that they ſhould continue in the fire, the fire of tribulation, and conſume not, burne not, yeeld not; but as though their bodies were burniſh't braſſe, ſhine onely the brighter for the fire; ſurely what can be the reaſon, but onely becauſe as the Lord was in the buſh, and ſo it conſumed not, ſo the Lord was in theſe buſhes, theſe weak Apoſtles, and they conſumed not?</p>
            <p>In the third of <hi>Daniel,</hi> the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Governours, Captains, and the Kings Councellours, all flocked to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, to ſee thoſe men upon whoſe bodies the fire had no power; they thought that a wonder; ſurely I know not whether it be a greater wonder, that the bodies of the Apoſtles, fleſh and blood like other men,<note place="margin">1 Peter 1.4.</note> that fiery tryall whereof St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeakes ſhould have no power upon them, ſhould not drive them to impatience, not to deſiſt or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert their Evangelical callings, but
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:114709:36"/>hold out 20, 30, 40 years together, unto the death, and in death: <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> was a godly Saint, and yet dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to a little impatience, that he was weary of his calling through the vexful behaviour of the Jews; <hi>If thou deale thus with me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 11.15.</note> 
               <hi>kill me I pray thee out of hand. Elias</hi> was a godly Saint, yet driven to a little impatience, when the ſtorme fell ſo fierce upon him; <hi>It is enough, now, O Lord, take away my life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 19.4.</note> 
               <hi>for I am not better then my fathers: Job</hi> was a Saint, who like him? and yet driven to a great deale of impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience; when he opened his mouth and curſed his day, <hi>Let the day pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh wherein I was borne,</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">Job. 3.</note> for a whole Chapter together. But where do we ever read that all the afflictions the world could heap upon them, put the Apoſtles into any impatience, or that their ſpirits were any whit broken, or their hearts dejected with them? nay it broke their hearts when others pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyed them, and would have had them favoured themſelves in Chriſts
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:114709:37"/>ſufferings; <hi>What meane you to weep and breake my heart?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 21.13 Act. 20.22.24.</note> 
               <hi>for I am rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy not onely to be bound, but alſo to dye,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And now behold I go bound in the ſpirit to Jeruſalem; But none of theſe things move me, neither count I my life deare unto my ſelfe,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And I take pleaſure in infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites,</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.10.</note> whence could they have this patience, nay this joy in all their tribulations, but from the power of the Holy Ghoſt? And therefore I marvell not that St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould ſo often urge this for an evident proofe of the truth of his miniſtry, his Apoſtleſhip, his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel that he preached, namely his <hi>patience</hi> and indefatigable enduring of all miſery and all affliction for the Goſpels ſake;<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.4. and 11.23 &amp;c. Gal. 6.17. Col. 4.18. 2 Cor. 4.7. and 10.</note> 
               <hi>In all things appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving our ſelves as the Miniſters of God, in much patience,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And from henceforth let no man trouble me, for I bear in my body the marks of the Lord Jeſus;</hi> And <hi>Remember my bonds.</hi> Well, I will conclude this with his reaſoning, <hi>we have this treaſure in earthen veſſels, that the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:114709:37"/>excellency of the power may be of God and not of us; alwayes bearing about in the body the dying of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, that the life alſo of Jeſus might be made manifeſt in our body.</hi> That it may appeare that Jeſus Chriſt is alive indeed, by giving ſuch ſtrength and power to ſuch a frail creature as <hi>Paul</hi> otherwiſe of himſelfe was; for that it is not to be underſtood of the life of glory to be manifeſted afterwards in the body, but ſo as it is already expounded, the drift and circumſtances ſhew. That the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of the power, &amp;c. in our mortall body, &amp;c. and becauſe in the fourteenth verſe he proceeds there to that ſenſe.</p>
            <div n="51" type="page">
               <p>Sixthly, Grace of <hi>tendereſt love and affection</hi> to the Salvation (if they could) of the whole world, to the Salvation of thoſe they never ſaw nor heard of before; to the Salvation of thoſe that it coſt them many a long tedious journey to come into them; to the Salvation of thoſe, that when they came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, gave them but cold
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:114709:38"/>entertainment, even ſought their death that came to bring them the word of life; ſuch love, whence could they have it, but from this power of the Holy Ghoſt? Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der but how cold and back-ward men are in this buſineſs, to build up one another, even neighbour his neighbour, and friend his freind in their Salvations; and ſay if theſe men muſt not needs have been acted and moved with ſomething in them more then fleſh and blood, that made them ſo zealous and earneſt for the Salvation of the whole world, of the unknowne world, the remote world, the injurious world, that ſought their deaths as much as they did their lives:</p>
               <p>Take a ſcantling of this their earneſt zeale and love to every Souls Salvation in St. <hi>Paul;</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, In St. <hi>Pauls</hi> ſollicitous <hi>care</hi> and feare; nothing ſo full of care and feare for anothers good as love; None ſo loving therefore as St. <hi>Paul,</hi> that had ſuch cares, and fears, and jealouſies in his heart as
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:114709:38"/>touching others Salvations;<note place="margin">2 Cor. 7.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Without were fightings, within were fears:</hi> Within fears, namely, leſt by ſome means men ſhould be tempted and drawne away again from the faith:<note place="margin">Gal. 4.19. 2 Cor. 11.2. and 28. Col. 2.1.</note> And <hi>I am jealous over you with a godly jealouſie;</hi> And <hi>beſides thoſe things that are without, that which cometh upon me dayly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 3.1.</note> 
                  <hi>the care of all the Churches.</hi> And <hi>I wiſh you knew what great conflict,</hi> namely of feare and care, <hi>I have for you;</hi> And <hi>for this cauſe when I could no longer forbeare,</hi> namely for care and fear about you:</p>
               <p>Secondly, See it in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> wiſe and ſtudious diligence, by art and by induſtry,<note place="margin">1 Col. 28.</note> ſtriving if he could to win every Soul; <hi>Though I be free from all men, yet have I made my ſelf ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to all,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.19.</note> 
                  <hi>that I might gain the more; that we may preſent every man perfect.</hi> &amp;c. Nothing ſo painfull and devicefull of any courſe to ſpeede as love.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, See it in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt obteſtations and entreaties that men would regard themſelves, and that which makes for their own Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations;
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:114709:39"/>no ſo humble a ſupplicant as true love: the tender mother would beg it on her knees at her ſons hand, that he would reclaime, and know his own good: ſo St. <hi>Paul</hi> moſt humbly beſeeches all, that they would know their own good, know the things that belong unto their own peace; <hi>Now then we are Embaſſadors in Chriſt;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.20. and 2.6.</note> 
                  <hi>we pray you in Chriſts ſtead be ye recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to God;</hi> And <hi>we then as workers together with him, beſeech you alſo, that ye receive not the grace of God in vaine.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.1.</note> And <hi>Now I Paul my ſelf beſeech you by the meekneſs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and gentleneſs of Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>To name one place more for all; <hi>If there be therefore any Conſolation in Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 2.1.</note> 
                  <hi>if any comfort of love,</hi> &amp;c. what would beg ſo hard for no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther boone, but onely that men would know the things that belong to their own peace; but onely Love?</p>
               <p>Fourthly, See it in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant thanks and prayers for thoſe whom God hath vouchſafed
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:114709:39"/>to call unto the participation of his heavenly truth: It is no ſmall mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of love that makes him ſo ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of others eternall good: others that what were they to him, but onely that they were the Sons of <hi>Adam;</hi> ſo ſenſible as to be ſo abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant in thanks to God for that bleſſing unto them, and in prayers to God for the continuance of it. Moſt of his Epiſtles begin with theſe thanks and prayers; Firſt,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.8. 1 Cor. 1.4. Epheſ. 1.15. Phil. 1.3. Col. 1.3. 1 Theſ. 1.2.</note> 
                  <hi>I thank my God through Jeſus Chriſt for you all, that your faith is ſpoken thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the world;</hi> And <hi>I thanke my God alwayes on your behalfe for the grace of God which is given by Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, See it in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſpirit when at any time men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined and went backward in the way of grace; <hi>Out of much affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and anguiſh of heart I wrote unto you with many tears;</hi> And <hi>who is weake, and I am not weake?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 2.4.</note> 
                  <hi>who is offended, and I burn not?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 11.29.</note> And <hi>I feare lest when I come among you, my God ſhall humble me among you,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:114709:40"/>and that I ſhall bewaile many that have ſinned already.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.21.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Sixthly, See it in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comforted and revived ſpirit again at the good news of the mens thri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and proſpering in the way of grace;<note place="margin">2 Cor. 7.4.</note> 
                  <hi>I am filled with comfort, I am exceeding joyfull in all our tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation;</hi> And,<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 3.7.</note> 
                  <hi>When Timotheus came from you, we were comforted over you in all our affliction and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe by your faith.</hi> And ſo St. <hi>John,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">3 John 4.</note> 
                  <hi>I have no greater joy then to heare that my children walke in truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seventhly, See it in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercenarineſs ſo far that he is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, yea glad, very glad to ſpend and to be ſpent for mens Salvations, yea, thoſe that the more abundantly he loves them, the leſſe perhaps he may be beloved again; <hi>I ſeeke not yours but you;</hi> And, <hi>I will very gladly ſpend</hi> (my wordly means if I had any) <hi>and be ſpent</hi> (quite exhauſt forth ſtrength and ſpirits in laborious endeavours) <hi>for you.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.15.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Eighthly, See it in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſs,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:114709:40"/>not thus to ſpend goods, and ſtrength, and ſpirits, but even life it ſelfe for mens Salvations, being <hi>affectionately deſirous of you;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 2.8.</note> and in the ſecond to the <hi>Philip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 2.17.</note> he raiſeth this willingneſs to dy for others Salvations into a joy to dy for them: <hi>Yea, and if I be offered upon the ſacrifice and ſervice of your faith, I joy and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce with you all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ninthly, See it in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſs not onely to dy for mens Salvations, but to be withheld for a while from fellowſhip with Chriſt in his glory, for the furtherance of others in their Salvations;<note place="margin">Phil. 1.23. 24. and 25.</note> 
                  <hi>I am in a ſtrait betwixt two, having a deſire to depart and to be with Chriſt which is far better, nevertheleſs to abide in the fleſh is more needfull for you,</hi> &amp;c. He muſt needs love much that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been in the third Heavens, and having had ſo many revelations of Chriſt, yet makes it a ſtrait and a hard choice, whether to chuſe, whether to be with Chriſt in bliſſe, or with poor loſt men in miſery
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:114709:41"/>for hope of his Salvation.</p>
               <p>Tenthly, See it in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſs not onely to be withheld a while from the fellowſhip of Chriſt in his glory, but to be accurſed for ever from this fellowſhip of Chriſt in his glory; for that is his meaning, to be accurſed from the fruition of his glory, not of his love. <hi>I ſay the truth in Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 9.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 2, 3.</note> 
                  <hi>I lye n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t, my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience alſo bearing me witneſſe in the holy Ghoſt, That I have great heavineſſe, and continuall ſorrow in my heart. For I could wiſh that my ſelf were accurſed from Chriſt, for my brethren, my kinſmen accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the fleſh.</hi> How ſerious and unfained, how ponderous and weighty his wiſh is, that it muſt needs be no leſſe then his eternall periſhing from Chriſt for their Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, his ſo ſolemne and ſacred atteſtations and proteſtations ſhow, <hi>I ſay the truth, I lye not,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Whence now (thinke you) could St. <hi>Paul</hi> have this grace of tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt love and affection to others Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, diſcovering it ſelf in his ſuch
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:114709:41"/>ſollicitous holy care and feare about them, in his ſo ſtudious diligence to edify (by all means that he could deviſe) every Soul in the way of Salvation, &amp;c? Whence but onely from the power of the holy Ghoſt?</p>
               <p>And now by this time, if you conſider all theſe; the grace of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary <hi>boldneſs,</hi> of extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary <hi>promptneſs of ſpeech and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> &amp;c. that ſhowed themſelves in the Apoſtles and firſt preachers of the Goſpel, you may know why the Apoſtle ſhould ſay, <hi>I would that yee knew what great conflict I have for you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Col. 2.1.</note> 
                  <hi>and for them of Laodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cea, and for as many as have not ſeene my face in the fleſh;</hi> Why for as many as had not ſeene his face in the fleſh? Why? becauſe they that by <hi>Pauls</hi> corporall preſence among them, had but experience of his holy boldneſs in the Lord, of his promtpneſs of ſpeech and wiſdome in the Lord, of his unſpeakeable pains and diligence in the Lord, &amp;c. they that thus ſaw his face in the fleſh, knew all his heavenly carriage
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:114709:42"/>and conſolation in the Lord, and in the word of his truth; they could not but be exceedingly perſwaded of the certainty thereof; ſo full of arguments was St. <hi>Pauls</hi> face, his bodily preſence and converſation in the Lord, to perſwade unto the certaine beliefe of the Goſpel which he preached. And hereupon it is from theſe arguments in his face eſpecially that he ſaith; <hi>If our Goſpel be hid,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.3.</note> 
                  <hi>it is hid to them that periſh;</hi> and that at his time of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture out of the world, he remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers <hi>Timothy</hi> of theſe arguments eſpecially in his face, <hi>But thou haſt fully knowne my doctrine, manner of life;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.10.14.</note> 
                  <hi>But continue thou in the things which thou haſt learned, knowing of whom thou haſt learned them;</hi> viz. of him that hath made them good by ſo many good arguments in his face. O that our people could but ſee thus arguments in our faces to confirme them in the truth of the Goſpel. But alas, our faces, our faces are the confuſion rather and confutation of the Goſpel, then the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:114709:42"/>confirmation of it; rather enough to make infidels then converts; ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther enough to offend the ſtrong, then to ſtrengthen the weak. If the Goſpel were now to be planted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, all the miracles in the world (I think) would not make it take, while our moralls are that they are. A miracle may ſtrike a little won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derment at firſt; but good morality it ſinkes, it ſoakes to the heart; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſneſs may fay, a miracle is from the Divel; but who can ſay that good morality is from the Divel? I meane, Univerſall good morality; for otherwiſe the Divel and his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine may have a ſhred of morali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, a little good morality neare the liſt, but he is never good thorowout the whole cloath as 'twere, the whole body of morality;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chryſ.</hi> in 1 Cor. Hom. 3. and 6.</note> but feele him a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle farther neere the rig, and you ſhal ſee the Divell to be the Divell for all his good morality near the liſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, whence had the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles that extraordinory grace of confirming their doctrine by mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, but from the power of the holy
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:114709:43"/>Ghoſt coming upon them? 'tis true indeed, that the Divell and his Diſciple the magician may goe far in doing things that mans reaſon would wonder at, elſe would not God have ſaid; <hi>If there ariſe a Prophet, and give you a ſigne or a wonder.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 13.1.</note> Nor would our Saviour have ſaid of the falſe Chriſts, and falſe Prophets; that they ſhould do ſuch great ſignes and wonders, <hi>that if it were poſſible they ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the very elect.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matt. 24.24.</note> Nor St. <hi>Paul</hi> of Antichriſt, that <hi>his coming ſhould be with all powers, and ſignes, and lying wonders.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.9.</note> Nor St. <hi>John</hi> of the ſame, that <hi>out of his mouth proceeded three uncleane ſpirits like frogs, which ſhould be the ſpirits of Divels workings miracles.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 16.13, 14.</note> But yet though they may goe far, yet they cannot poſſibly reach to the height of mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles that our Saviour and his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples did; elſe would not our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour have ſaid, <hi>Go, and ſhow</hi> John <hi>the things you ſee and heare;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 2.22.</note> 
                  <hi>the Blind reccive their ſight, the lame walke,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 11.5.</note> &amp;c. And, <hi>I have a greater
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:114709:43"/>witneſſe then that of</hi> John, <hi>the works which the Father hath given me to finiſh, the ſame beare witneſſe of me;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 5.36.</note> And, <hi>If I do not the work of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther believe me not.</hi> And,<note place="margin">John 10.37.</note> 
                  <hi>believe me that I am in the Father, and the Father in me;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 14.11,</note> 
                  <hi>or elſe believe me for the very works ſake.</hi> And, <hi>If I had not done among them the wirks which none other did,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 15.24.</note> 
                  <hi>they had not had ſin,</hi> &amp;c. Nor would the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt have ſaid of the miracles of the Apoſtles, that they went forth and preached every where, the Lord, working with them and confirming the word with ſignes following; <hi>In my name ſhall they caſt out Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mark 16.17.</note> &amp;c. Nor St. <hi>Luke,</hi> that <hi>with great power gave the Apoſtles wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Reſurrection of the Lord Jeſus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 4.33.</note> Theſe things would not have been ſaid of the miracles of our Saviour and his Diſciples, if the Divell and his Diſciple the Magician could have done as much; it had been very vaine, nay very dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous too for our Saviour, and his Diſciples to have proved their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:114709:44"/>by no other means then which a deceiver by the help of a Divell might prove his falſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine by, and therefore ſome ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialneſs there was in the miracles which our Saviour and his Diſciples did, over and above what the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian or the greateſt <hi>Beelzebub</hi> of all could do, as it is well obſerved, <hi>God wrought ſpeciall miracles by the hands of Paul;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 19.11. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> not ordinary ones, ſuch as Mount-Bank-Magicians or Mount-Bank Divels could do.</p>
               <p>And that there was ſuch <hi>ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> in them,</p>
               <p>Conſider, Firſt, from the nature of the things, becauſe all the Divels wonders are but deluſions and jug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glements, making things appeare which are not, by corrupting ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the imagination, ſometimes the ſenſe, ſometimes the aire, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the object; or elſe if they be realities, true things ſuch as they ſeeme, then they are not above the pitch of nature, but either the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels ſleight of hand onely, ſuddenly through the agility that is in him to
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:114709:44"/>bring or remove off the ſtage a thing that had the being elſewhere before, as he might doe with the frogs and ſerpents before <hi>Pharaoh;</hi> or elſe they are done by the ſecret qualities of nature, the Divell know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing better the ſecret qualities and operations of all ſimples then man does, and being nimbler of the ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to lay the ſimples together then man can be, and ſo that which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed nature works, ſeemes above nature to us, becauſe we ſee not the plaine and uſuall courſe of nature effecting it; and thus the Divell may raiſe ſtormes, and do ſome petty cures, &amp;c. But the right miracles, ſuch as Chriſt and his Apoſtles wrought, ſurpaſſed all created power of nature bodily or Ghoſtly, ſo that no creature corporall or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporall could have done them either ſimply not at all, as raiſing of the dead, or curing ſome kind of incurable infirmities; or elſe not in an inſtant ſo, as the curing of ſome kind of infirmities curable perhaps in nature, with uſe of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:114709:45"/>ſimples, but yet not in an inſtant, till the ſimples have time to work; whereas our Saviour and his Diſciples cured with a word in an inſtant. I will for example ſake name two miracles, one of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours, another of his Apoſtles, that it ſhall be plaine, that neither they were any deceit but truly done, nor could be done by any art Magick of the Divels.</p>
               <p>That of our Saviours ſhall be the curing of the blind man,<note place="margin">John 9.</note> which is plaine, that it was no impoſture or deceit, but a thing truly done, by the accurate ſearch of the Phariſees into it, who would not beleive it, till they examined it throughly, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and conjuring the parents about him; <hi>Is this your ſon whom ye ſay was borne blind?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 19.20.</note> 
                  <hi>and they anſwered, wee know that this is our ſon, and that he was borne blind:</hi> it was no deceit therefore, neither could it be done by any art Magick, but God muſt needs have a hand in it; This the very Phariſees confeſſe; Firſt, in their diviſion, how can a man
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:114709:45"/>that is a ſinner do ſuch miracles? Secondly, joyntly, when they ſay, <hi>Give God the praiſe,</hi> &amp;c. Again, the man that was cured was bold to ſay before them all, contradict him who could, <hi>Since the world began was it not heard,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 10.20.21.</note> 
                  <hi>that any man opened the eyes of one that was borne blind</hi> Again, the Jews when they were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, <hi>ſome ſaid that he had a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell, but other replyed, Can a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell open the eyes of the blind?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The example of the Apoſtles ſhall be that of their curing the lame man; And firſt,<note place="margin">Act. 3.</note> that it was not a deceit, but a thing truly done, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſayes the text,<note place="margin">verſe 10.</note> 
                  <hi>They knew it was he that ſate for Alms at the beautifull gate of the Temple;</hi> Nay, he was laid dayly, that the very bearers that brought him could wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe aſſuredly that it was he, and at a publick place the gate of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; nay the beautifull gate, where moſt company came: no deceit therefore but a thing truly done, nor nothing could do it but a power Divine, therefore doth the ſpirit
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:114709:46"/>of God ſet out all circumſtances, of the lameneſs, of the cure, of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples behaviour upon the cure; Of the <hi>lameneſs,</hi> that he was lame from his mothers wombe, ſo lame that he could not ſo much as help him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a whit with crutch, but he muſt even plainly be carryed; ſo lame that his lameneſs continued forty years together: Of the <hi>cure,</hi> that it was meerly by a word, <hi>In the name of Jeſus Chriſt of Nazareth, riſe up and walke;</hi> that it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, <hi>and immediately his feet and ancle bones received ſtrength;</hi> perfectly, <hi>and he leaping up, ſtood and walked,</hi> &amp;c. Of the <hi>peoples behaviour</hi> after, that it was ſo great a miracle, that <hi>they were fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with wonder and amazement,</hi> that they ran all together unto them, that as it is, Act. 4.21. <hi>all men glorified God for that which was done;</hi> they could not imagine that it could be any thing elſe but Gods own work; yea, ſo pregnant were all circumſtances, that it was a thing truly done, and ſupernaturally done;
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:114709:46"/>that the councell caſting their heads together, could not cavill at theſe two points;<note place="margin">Act. 4.16.</note> 
                  <hi>what ſhall we do to theſe men, for that indeed a notable miracle hath been done by them,</hi> &amp;c? No queſtion therefore our Saviours and his Diſciples miracles had ſome <hi>ſpecialneſs</hi> in them, elſe having ſuch enemies to pry and enquire into them, they would eaſily have been cavill'd againſt and cryed down, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as nothing but fraud, or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Magick; as they the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle-mongers now a dayes in <hi>Italy</hi> are not ſo buſy to forge a miracle, as the Jew that lives among them is to find out their forgery, that either it is nothing but fraud, or nothing but Magick; I take it for granted therefore, that all the Divels in Hell could not have done the miracles.</p>
               <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">Mat. 11.5. Act. 5.12. and 9.33. and 14.8. and 19.11.</note> that there was ſome <hi>ſpecialneſs</hi> in them above all Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick, conſider from the prevailing with thoſe that had been exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bewitched with all Magick before; ſurely they plainly ſaw ſome ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialneſs in them above their former
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:114709:47"/>Magick, elſe they would not by theſe miracles have left it and come off to the Apoſtles. <hi>Samaria</hi> was a City exceedingly bewitched with the ſorceryes of <hi>Simon-Magus,</hi> and that a long time, and that from the leaſt to the greateſt of them, and that in ſuch a manner that they ſaid of him; This man is <hi>the great power of God;</hi> And yet this ſo bewitched a City at the hearing and ſeeing the miracles that <hi>Philip</hi> did, ſo far were they beyond all the ſorceryes of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Magus,</hi> were converted unto the faith; Nay the great wonder-worker himſelf, <hi>Simon-Magus won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd</hi> (ſayes the text) <hi>beholding the miracles and ſignes which were done,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 8.18.</note> and himſelf became, or ſeemed to become a convert; he ſaw that <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lips</hi> miracles were far beyond all his Mount-bank trikes; his were mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vells or farlayes for fooles, but <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lips</hi> were miracles, miracles indeed.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that there was ſome <hi>ſpecialneſs</hi> in them above Magick, conſider from the victory over the Magicians themſelves; <hi>There was
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:114709:47"/>a famous Sorcerer called Elymas,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 13.</note> i. e. <hi>a ſorcerer</hi> for his notableneſs that way: Now this <hi>Elymas</hi> had tampered with <hi>Sergius Paulus</hi> the Deputy of the Country, and when the Deputy ſent for <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas,</hi> this Sorcerer <hi>withſtood them</hi> (namely <hi>as Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres</hi> withſtood Moſes by his ſorceryes) <hi>and ſought to turn the Deputy from the faith;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Timot. 3.8.</note> but what ſayes Paul? <hi>O full of all ſubtility and all miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheife, thou child of the Divell,</hi> &amp;c. cutting words, not fearing his ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceryes a whit, you ſee; and <hi>now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the hand of the Lord is upon thee, and thou ſhalt be blind,</hi> &amp;c. a ſtrange effect following; Imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately he was blind, ſtark blind, ſo <hi>that be ſought for ſome to lead him by the hand. Pauls</hi> ſetting his eyes onely on him made the great ſorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer loſe his eyes, all his ſorcery could not withſtand a looke of <hi>Pauls</hi> eyes, ſo ſtrange was the foile of this ſorcerer ſeeking to them, that the Deputy when he ſaw what was done, believed. Was there not
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:114709:48"/>therefore ſome ſpecialneſs in the power that the Apoſtles had, above the power of the Magician? when ſuch an Arch-magician was ſo foiled, foiled to the ſtriking of himſelf ſtark blind; this was like the foile of <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoks</hi> Magicians by <hi>Moſes;</hi> ſtriking the Magicians themſelvs with bolls; they could not ſave their own skins,<note place="margin">Exo. 9.11.</note> 
                  <hi>the boile was upon the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, and upon all the Magicians;</hi> a thing purpoſely noted.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, That there was ſome <hi>ſpecialneſs</hi> in them as not done by any Magick, conſider from the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying every where by them the Kingdome of the Divels; the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell ſhould not have helped to have over-throwne utterly his own king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome by his own wonders; More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over how ſhould they be done by Magick, that every where where they came made all Magick be caſt away; as they that were converted by <hi>Pauls</hi> preaching and ſpeciall miracles,<note place="margin">Act. 19.19.</note> there ſpoken of, preſently caſhiered their Magick? <hi>They that uſed curious arts</hi> (Magick and the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:114709:48"/>like) <hi>they brought their bookes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and burned, them before all men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, For the Apoſtles mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles that there was ſome <hi>ſpecialneſs</hi> in them, and not done by Magick, Conſider from the holineſs of the doctrine not a little; The Divell would never have confirmed ſuch a pure and holy and heavenly Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine with his wonders, his works; the impiety, filthineſs, villany which Story ſhowes they required in their very work proves this; their very work being performed <hi>ſo much the more devoutly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tantò devotiùs quantò turpiùs,</hi> Aug. of Floras de Civitat. 2.27. and 4.</note> 
                  <hi>by how much the more filthily.</hi> And that alſo of <hi>Auſtin,</hi> ſhewes, asking the Gentiles why their Gods did not publikely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade unto life and good manners, inſpiring and appointing Prophets, and teachers for the ſame, but wholly neglected that?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibidem.</hi> 2.6</note> or if they gave rules of good life, it was but to ſome few ſpeciall ones in their private <hi>(Adytis)</hi> Cabinets, but let all vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany be uncontrouled publikely; <hi>They did the one, that the more honeſt
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:114709:49"/>who are but few might be enſnared;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Illud, ut honeſtiores qui pauci ſunt, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piantur; hoc, ne plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res qui ſunt turpiſſimi corrigian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. <hi>Ibid. 2.26.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and the other, that the moſt, who are diſhoneſt, might not be reformed.</hi> The Apoſtles miracles therefore were not done in the Divels name, the holineſs of their Doctrine ſhowes; when ſome ſaid of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour that he had a Divell, it was well anſwered, <hi>Theſe are not the words of him that hath a Divell.</hi> Theſe, ſuch holy and heavenly words that he had ſpoken hard be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>John</hi> 10. So if any ſhould ſay, that the Apoſtles had Divels, &amp; did the miracles they did in their names; read their words and their writings, and are theſe the words of them that have Divels, words of ſuch holineſs, ſuch heavenlyneſs, ſuch univerſall compleat goodneſs? the Divell indeed and his Doctrine may have a ſhred of goodneſs, a little good morality neare the liſt, &amp;c. but thorowout from liſt to liſt, how good and juſt and holy is the Apoſtles Doctrine? Give me but ſuch a Saint as the Apoſtles re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire by their Doctrine, and let
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:114709:49"/>malice and envy pick a hole if it can.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, that the Apoſtles mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles had ſome <hi>ſpecialneſs</hi> in them, and were not magicall; Conſider from this, that they were not won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders onely, but mercies; as curing the ſick, reſtoring ſight to the blind &amp;c. Whereas things done by Magick commonely had nothing in them, but a little admiration, no mercy; as for <hi>Attilius</hi> to cut a whet-ſtone a funder with a raſor; for a <hi>veſtal virgin</hi> to draw water in a ſive; for another to pull a ſhip up <hi>Tyber</hi> with her girdle when with Cables all the company beſides could not make her ſtir; for <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet</hi> to make the moon ſeeme to come in at his ſleeve, &amp;c. Such wonderments, toyiſh wonderments does the Divell ordinarely work; but where are his mercies, his curing the ſick, &amp;c? indeed ſometimes he cures ſome ſick,<note place="margin">Postquam definunt laedere, &amp; curaſſe cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duntur; <hi>Tert. Apol.</hi>
                  </note> but it is but <hi>una ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demque manus,</hi> &amp;c. but healing where he hurt; when they ceaſe to hurt, they are thought to heale:
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:114709:50"/>as if I ſhould eaſe, by pulling away the pin that I thruſt into another ſides; it is but thus healing where he hurt; or elſe in ſome leſſer diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes perhaps that are within his skill, healing ſometimes that he may hurt; wounding the Soul to the heart, through healing the ripled skin of the body. And thus it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears that the miracles of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles had ſome <hi>ſpecialneſs</hi> in them, and were done by no other Magick, then that of our Saviours, <hi>Yet ſhall receive power of the holy Ghoſt,</hi> &amp;c. And if ſo, then that our Saviour is not in the grave, but riſen indeed, that could ſend this power of the holy Ghoſt upon them.</p>
               <p>I will end this point with St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin;</hi> If any ſay that theſe ſpeciall miracles were not indeed wrought by the Apoſtles to confirme Chriſts Reſurrection and aſcenſion;<note place="margin">Hoc nobis unum gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum ſufficit, quòd ea terrarum orbis ſine ullis mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culis credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit.</note> This one great miracle ſufficeth us, that the world believed theſe things without miracles; There are theſe incredible things ſayes he; One, that Chriſt is riſen from the dead, and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:114709:50"/>aſcended bodily into heaven: Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that the world ſhould have believed ſo incredible a thing; A third, incredibleſt of all, that a few ſilly obſcure meane fellows ſhould perſwade the world to this beliefe: either therefore they wrought ſome ſpeciall miracles to perſwade the world thereunto,<note place="margin">Et Eloquia perſuaden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium mira fuerunt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta non verba.</note> 
                  <hi>(and their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſive arguments were wondrous works, not words)</hi> or elſe this is the miracle of all miracles, that the world ſhould believe thoſe few ſilly men without miracles.<note place="margin">De civitat. 22.7. <hi>Quiſquis ergo adhuc prodigia ut credat in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirit, magnum eſt ipſe prodigium qui mundo credente non credit:</hi> 22.8.
<p>John 3.2. and 12.37; Aug. de Civit. Dei: 21.6. <hi>Vide quandam auream catenam apud Chryſ.</hi> in 1 Cor. Hom. 7.</p>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Whoſoever therefore doth yet require miracles, that he may believe, he not belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, when the world believeth, is himſelf a great miracle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, Whence had the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles that extraordinary grace of ſuch <hi>happy ſucceſſe</hi> in their preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in ſo ſhort a time to draw al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:114709:51"/>the world after them, to bring all to their lure, to make all dance after their pipe, whence but from this power of the holy Ghoſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on them, and making their words to be very charms unto the people? <hi>verily, verily,</hi> ſayes our Saviour to his Diſciples; <hi>he that believeth on me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 14.</note> 
                  <hi>the works that I do ſhall he do alſo, and greater works then theſe;</hi> now what are theſe grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter works? Our Saviour he cured all diſeaſes, and caſt out Divils, he raiſed the dead; what greater works did the Apoſtles? yes, the converſion of the world, and the ſubverſion every where of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome that is called the Prince of the world, were greater works; a farre greater work to raiſe up the dead world, then one dead <hi>Lazarus; Lazarus</hi> had been four dayes in the grave, and was ready to ſtinke, the world had ſtunke many and many years together in the grave of all Idolatries, impieties, luſts, wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, &amp;c. a farre greater work to caſt out Satan every where out of
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:114709:51"/>his Temples, out of his worſhip, out of the hearts of men that every where he poſſeſſed, then out of the bodies of a few Corporally poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; whence therefore could the Apoſtles do theſe greater works, but from the power of the holy Ghoſt, from the reaſon rendred in that text, <hi>becauſe I go unto my Futher.</hi> &amp;c. becauſe I cannot be deteyned in the grave<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but riſe again to have all power given me both in Heaven and in earth?</p>
               <p>Now conſider with me from ſome particulars, the greatneſs of his worke; by twelve men ſuch as they were, to convert a World ſuch as it was, to embrace a Doctrine ſuch as they preached; Conſider the greatneſs of this work, and then ſay my text is proved, <hi>But now is Chriſt-riſen from the dead,</hi> elſe this work could never have taken, that ſuch a <hi>doctrine,</hi> to ſuch a <hi>world,</hi> by ſuch <hi>twelve men</hi> ſhould have been effectually preached.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> Firſt, ſuch a <hi>Doctrine,</hi> a Doctrine that might have offended, as a new
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:114709:52"/>Doctrine, an incredible Doctrine, a Doctrine too high for the world wallowing in fleſh and blood, a Doctrine bringing the croſſe and perſecution after it, a Doctrine that for the enduring the croſſe, and for the crucifying their fleſh and blood gave no preſent promiſes; but the promiſes to envite unto the Goſpel, were future and in another world; a Doctrine that might have offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thus many wayes.</p>
               <p>Firſt, as a <hi>new Doctrine,</hi> that ſhould have overturned all their old Religion: no more the ſame rites, the ſame Ceremonies, the ſame Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, the ſame Temples, the ſame Gods that they and their predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors had ſo long time worſhipped, but all muſt be caſhierd, and a new upſtart tother-day Religion about one <hi>Jeſus of Nazareth,</hi> never heard of before, forſooth, muſt come in the roome; away with ſuch new Doctrine. Novelty, that in other things is pleaſing to the nature of man, is odious in Religion. The Divell knowes what he does when
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:114709:52"/>he ſeekes to caſt upon us by our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaryes the aſperſion of novelty, of a new Goſpel and new Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, new Bibles and new every thing; even the very old cobwebs in the Temple are ſacred, and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition is loth to have them bruſhed down, though they have venemous ſpiders in them, and webs of lawne might be hung in their roome; ſo odious is Novelty in Religion, and therefore firſt it might have offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as a <hi>new Doctrine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, as an <hi>incredible Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine;</hi> what credibleneſs that life and Salvation ſhould be preached in the name of a pretended God, borne but of a poor Jewiſh woman, brought up like a poor Carpenters ſon, crucified like a wicked malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, dead and buried like a weake man, and affirmed by almoſt the whole nation of the Jews to be yet under the power of death, when as but two or three obſcure fiſhermen and the like talke of his Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction? What credibleneſs in this Doctrine? Is it credible that he
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:114709:53"/>that was ſo borne, ſo bred, ſo cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, ſo dead and buried; and no talke but by a few obſcure Gali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laeans of his Reſurrection, that he ſhould be the onely God bleſſed for ever, principalities, and powers, and thrones, and dominions, and all the renowned Gods up and down the world, that our Fathers and our Preiſts and our Prophets have told us ſuch ſtrange things of ſhould be made ſubject to him? Nay, is it credible that he that was this great God would be ſo borne, ſo bred, ſo crucified, would ſo dye and be bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried? that majeſty would be cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with ſuch vileneſs, that power and omnipotency would dwell with ſuch weakneſs, that life and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality would embrace and ſhake hands with death and the grave? So incredible is this Doctrine, that all the cheife hereſies of old were either againſt the true Divinity of our Saviour, as the <hi>Arians, Photi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> &amp;c. or the true humanity, as the <hi>Simonians, Manichees, Marcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites,</hi> &amp;c. or the true union of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:114709:53"/>and humanity into one perſon, as the <hi>Neſtorians, Eutychians,</hi> &amp;c. ſo unworthy thought they it was, that the great God in one and the ſame perſon ſhould become man; or ſo overworthy that meane man ſhould in one and the ſame perſon become God: ſo that you may know our Saviour had good reaſon to ſay of <hi>Peters</hi> confeſſion,<note place="margin">Mat. 16.17.</note> 
                  <hi>whom do men ſay that I the ſon of man am?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Quodcun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Deo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignum eſt, mihi expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, &amp;c. Natus est, Dei Filius, non pudet quia puden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum est; &amp; moriuus est Dei Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius, prorſus credibile est quia inep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt; &amp; ſepultus reſurrexit, certum est, quia impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibile eſt. <hi>Tert. de Carne Chriſti.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Thou art Chriſt the ſon of the living God;</hi> This is ſuch high Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, that he that was the ſon of man, he the ſame ſhould be the ſon of the living God; that our Saviour might well ſay, <hi>Fleſh and blood hath not revealed this unto thee.</hi> And this, that <hi>Chriſt crucified ſhould be the Saviour of the world;</hi> that <hi>Paul</hi> might well ſay, <hi>we preach Chriſt crucified unto the Jews a ſtumbling blocke; and unto the Greeks fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Whatſoever ſeemes unworthy of God, is for me expedient,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>the ſon of God is borne, I am not aſhamed of it, becauſe it ſeemes a thing not to be aſhamed of; and the ſon of God
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:114709:54"/>dyed, this is altogether credible, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ſeemes abſurd; and after he was buried, he roſe again, this is certaine, becauſe it ſeemes impoſſible.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And therefore, Secondly, it might have offended as an incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Doctrine, incredible that he that ſeemed to be but a poore weake crucified man, ſhould be the great God and Saviour of all; or as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible that he that was this great God and Saviour of all, would be a poore weake crucified man.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, As a Doctrine <hi>too high</hi> for the world to embrace, wallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in fleſh and blood; what high Doctrine was it to teach the proud world, the humility of Chriſt Jeſus? the uncharitable world the love of their very enemies? the unchaſt world the reſtraint even of an unchaſt looke? the revengefull world, not to reſiſt evill, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther if one ſmite him on the right cheeke, to turn to him the left alſo? The ſturdy ſtomackfull world to ſeeke reconcilement with ones bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? the gripple pinch-penny
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:114709:54"/>world to be liberall in almes? the covetous carking world not to lay up treaſures on earth, not to be thoughtfull about to morrow, but let to morrow take thought for it ſelfe? in a word, the profane diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute world to tuck up their loyns of their mind, and to be ſober, and walke unto a preciſe circumſpect walking in all godlineſs and hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty? Say any one now, even the beſt here that conſiders from the experience of the reliques of his own corruption yet in him, what a hard thing it is for the proud ſpirit to be taught the humility of Chriſt Jeſus, &amp;c ſay if the doctrine of the Goſpel might not well have offended, as a Doctrine <hi>too high</hi> for the world, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, As a Doctrine <hi>bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtill the croſſe</hi> and perſecution with it. No ſooner was any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted to the Goſpel, but preſently blows flew thick about his ears, and the Divell raiſed up a ſtorme of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution againſt him, even a mans enemies proved they of his own houſhold, the father betraying the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:114709:55"/>ſon to death, &amp;c. ſo inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble an attendant of the Goſpel in the primitive times was the croſſe and perſecution, that the Apoſtles ſtill where they preached the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, preached the Doctrine alſo of enduring tribulation; So <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> went through <hi>Lyſtra, Ice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium</hi> and <hi>Antioch.</hi> confirming the Souls of the Diſciples and exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them to continue in the faith. And that <hi>wee muſt through much tribulation enter into the Kingdom of God:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 14.22.</note> 
                  <hi>So your ſelves know that wee are appointed thereunto, to endure af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, for verily when we were with you, we told you before, that we ſhould ſuffer tribulation, even as it came to paſſe;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 3.3, 4. 2 Tim. 3.12.</note> So <hi>all that will live godly in the world, ſhall ſuffer perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution:</hi> Say therefore, they that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what the wiſdom of the fleſh is, namely, to thinke it good ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a whole skin, good hearkning to S. <hi>Peters</hi> Counſell to our <hi>Saviour,</hi> telling how <hi>many things he ſhould ſuffer at Jeruſalem, and there be kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Spare thy ſelf,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> let not theſe
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:114709:55"/>and theſe things befall thee.<note place="margin">Matt. 16.22.</note> Say if the Doctrine of the Goſpel might not alſo have offended, as a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctirne bringing the croſſe with it.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, As a Doctrine that <hi>invited</hi> to all that hard matter, and hard task of the croſſe, by no other promiſes then future of another world; it ſhould coſt them here, if they would be right Chriſtians, the denying of themſelves, the mortifying of their pleaſures, their plucking out their right eyes, their cutting off their right hands and feet, &amp;c. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it would coſt them the enduring the croſſe, the ſuffering ſhame, the going ſtill with their lives in their hands; but reward here they ſhould looke for none, onely believe if they would,<note place="margin">Matt. 5.12. Matt. 19.28. Luke 14.14. Act. 3.19.</note> 
                  <hi>great ſhould be their reward in Heaven; great in that regeneration, great in that Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the juſt, great in thoſe dayes of refreſhing from the preſence of the Lord; great in that coming of his to be glorified in his Saints and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of all them that believe;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 1.10. Col. 3.3.</note> 
                  <hi>your life is hid with Chriſt in God.</hi> But
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:114709:56"/>in the meane time they muſt poſſeſſe their Souls in patience, live by faith, work all things, and endure all things, as ſeeing him that is inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and looking for that reward which is inviſible; what a <hi>ſnub</hi> and hinderance thinke you was this like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to have been unto fleſh and blood, hankering ſtill after the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent things, and loving to believe no more then it ſees? what a ſnub and hinderance from embracing that doctrine that invited unto ſuch high doings, and ſuch deep ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, upon promiſes onely hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and in another world? whereof they had no other aſſurance then that;<note place="margin">Heb. 11.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Now faith is the ſubſtance of things hoped for, and the evidence of things not ſeene;</hi> and therefore whence but from the power of the holy Ghoſt could ſuch a doctrine of theirs as this have taken? a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine that might have offended as a <hi>new Doctrine,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> Secondly, whence not onely ſuch a doctrine, but to ſuch a world, a world ſo Captiv'd under Satan, ſo
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:114709:56"/>corrupted in manners, ſo rooted and habituate in former ſuperſtitious cuſtome, whence could ſuch a world have been by the preaching of this doctrine, plucked out of the hands of Satan, out of the corruption of their own manners, out of the habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuateneſs of ſuperſtitious cuſtome, but by the power of him that was riſen from the dead?</p>
               <p>Firſt, A world ſo <hi>captived under Satan;</hi> how enthralled the world was to Satan before the preaching of the Goſpel, beſides theſe texts of Scripture,<note place="margin">Act. 26.18.</note> 
                  <hi>I ſend thee to the Gentiles to open their eyes and to turn them from the power of Satan unto God;</hi> And <hi>wherein in times paſt ye walked according to the Prince of the power of the aire;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epeſ. 2.2. Epheſ. 6.12.</note> And <hi>we wreſtle not againſt fleſh and blood,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 John 5.19. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>but againſt principalities, againſt the rulers of the darkneſs of this world,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>we know that the whole world lyes in wickedneſs.</hi> Beſides theſe and the like texts of Scripture, how en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thralled to Satan the world was, common experience ſhowed; eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:114709:57"/>where he had his Temples, his oracles, they were much made of, his worſhip nothing was too deare for it; <hi>He eat the fatt of their ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, and drunke the wine of their drinke offerings;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 32.38.</note> nay even often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he drunke the blood of their ſons and daughters, whom they ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed unto Divels; how thinke you now would he beſtirre himſelfe ſtill to hold poſſeſſion, how loath would he be to let this embondaged world that had beene his old and good ſervant ſo long, goe out of his clutches? Conſider the <hi>ſpirituall Pharaoh</hi> by the <hi>Egyptian Pharaoh;</hi> how loath was he to let the embon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daged Iſrael goe? when their deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance was once a foot<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he tryes all his wits and might to keep them ſtill, he doubles their tasks, he ſets over them ſeverall taskmaſters, and if they muſt needs goe and ſacrifice to their God, let them do it in the land; or if out of the land, then let them not goe farre; or if farre, let onely them that are men, but their little ones ſtay behind; or if their
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:114709:57"/>little ones muſt needs go, yet their flocks and herds let them ſtay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind; or if all muſt go not a hoofe be left behind, then the Charets of Egypt muſt be muſter'd up, and an army royall raiſed to purſue them at the red Sea, and ſeeke to bring them back again, ſo loath is <hi>Pharaoh</hi> to let imbondaged Iſrael go. How loath thinke you then the <hi>ſprituall Pharaoh</hi> would be to let the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bondaged world goe? and how would he try all his wit and his might to have ſome little hold of the world ſtill? or if they would needs goe fully out of his power, then he would raiſe up terrible per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution againſt ſuch as were eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped his hands, and ſeeke by fire and ſword to bring them back again into their old bondage; a world there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo captiv'd under Satan, how could it have been brought unto the obedience of the Goſpel,<note place="margin">Luke 10.18. and 11.22. 1 Cor. 12.3.</note> but by the power of him that was riſen from the dead?</p>
               <p>Secondly, A world ſo <hi>corrupted in manners;</hi> how groſſely corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:114709:58"/>in manners the world was before the goſpel ſo ſainted many of them, let theſe places ſhow;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.11.</note> 
                  <hi>And ſuch</hi> (namely fornicatours, &amp;c.) <hi>were ſome of you; but ye are ſanctified,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And you hath he quickned who were dead in treſpaſſes and ſins.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.1.3. Col. 3.5.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Among whom wee had our converſation in times paſt. Mortify therefore your members which are upon the earth, fornication uncleannes,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>in the which ye alſo walked ſometime when ye lived in them.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.3, 4.</note> 
                  <hi>For the time paſt of our life may ſuffice us to have Wrought the will of the Gentiles,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>wherein they thinke it ſtrange that you run not with them into the ſame exceſſe of riot;</hi> A world thus cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted in manners, whence could it on the ſudden for a great part of it have been ſo changed, ſo ſainted, but from the power of him that was riſen from the dead? whence could ſuch ſinks and filthy puddles have become on the ſudden clear chryſtall waters? whence ſuch rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſtinking dunghils on the ſudden become beds of ſpices and all ſweet
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:114709:58"/>fragrant flowers? whence ſuch pezzled, leprous, loathſome crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures on the ſudden become ſo cleane and ſuch wonders of beauty? In the laſt place that I cited, you have this, <hi>wherein they think it ſtrange,</hi> &amp;c. Strange indeed, that you that were brothers of the ſame wicked crue, ſwine wallowing in the ſame mire, beetles living and feeding among the ſame dung; ſtrange that you ſhould be ſuch altered creatures on the ſudden! yeſterday very ſwills in all brutiſh drunkenneſs, to day very paterns of all ſobriety; yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day very brothellers and ſtews-mates, to day very ſamples of chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; yeſterday very muck-wormes for the world; to day very Angels for heavenlyneſs and contempt of the world! There are ſome known ſwills in the world old in drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſome known brothellers old in whoring and adultery, ſome known muck-wormes old in very very muck-mungring, and meere meere worldiſhneſs, Now if one by ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but two or three words to theſe
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:114709:59"/>in the name of God, ſhould ſo alter one of theſe knowne ſwills, brothel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, muck-wormes, that for ever after they ſhould be very ſamples of all ſobriety, chaſtity, liberality, &amp; Chriſtian contempt of the world; would not all ſay, that ſurely God had a hand in it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and it was done by a Divine power? it is the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which ſaint <hi>Aug.</hi> preſſeth at large to prove a Divine power in planting the Goſpel;<note place="margin">Si dicitur avaris, Nolite vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis condere theſauros in terrâ, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Si dicitur luxurioſis qui ſemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in Carne, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>If it be ſaid to the covetous, lay not up for your ſelves treaſures on earth,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>if to the luxurious, they that ſow to the fleſh,</hi> &amp;c. A world therefore ſo cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted in manners, whence could it have been reformed but from a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine power?</p>
               <p>Thirdly, A world ſo <hi>rooted and habituate in ſuperſtitious cuſtemes;</hi> they and their Fathers, and their Fore-Fathers had ſo many years together worſhipped theſe and theſe Gods they had prayed unto them in their diſtreſſes and adverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, they had bleſſed them in their proſperities; they had deprecated
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:114709:59"/>their anger, when any judgment was upon them, famine, ſword ſickneſs; they had magnified their goodneſs when the judgment was removed, they had aſcribed all their good and all their ill fortune unto them; they had heard ſtrange things of their oracles and of their miracles; They had built them long agoe, for the credit and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity they gat in the world, ſtately Temples; Offered them rich gifts, made them goodly images, &amp;c. they ſaw the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r very Kings and great ones bowed unto them, their very Concellours and wiſe men worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, their very Philoſophers and learnedſt Clarks adored them, their prieſts and and religious vota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries were exceedingly religious about them; and muſt they now caſhiere all theſe? muſt now twelve vagrant wandring ſneakes cry downe that which for ſo many ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations together hath been held for good in the world? muſt they now throw down thoſe Temples, breake down thoſe images, deſtroy
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:114709:60"/>thoſe Altars, ungod thoſe Gods that ſuch antiquity hath counted venerable? muſt a tent-maker tell them now that their great <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Mercurius</hi> are but vanities? <hi>We preach unto you that you ſhould turn from theſe vanities unto the living God;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 14.15.</note> Muſt the tent-maker teach the very <hi>Athenians</hi> their fondneſs about theſe things?<note place="margin">Act. 17.22.</note> 
                  <hi>Yee men of Athens, I perceive that you are too ſuperſtitious?</hi> muſt the world now be taught by him that <hi>an Idol is nothing in the world,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 8.6.</note> and that <hi>there is but one God the Father, of whom are all things?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.20.</note> and that <hi>that which they ſacrifice to Idols, they ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to Divels?</hi> How ſtrong and ſtiffe preſcription and cuſtom is in matter of Religion?<note place="margin">Gen. 31.34.</note> 
                  <hi>Rachels</hi> ſteal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away her Fathers images; Nay after that,<note place="margin">Gen. 35.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Jacobs</hi> houſhold having yet ſtrange Gods among them; Nay after that, the Iſraelites wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping the Gods in Egypt; nay after that alſo, their worſhipping the ſame Gods when by <hi>Joſhua</hi> they were brought into <hi>Canaan;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 24.14.</note> ſhow
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:114709:60"/>how ſtrong and ſtiffe in matter of Religion Cuſtome is; what was that the Samaritan woman ſtood upon, but this?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>John. 4.20.</hi> Patres no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtri in hoe monte, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>our Fathers wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped in this Mountaine;</hi> What was it that they objected againſt <hi>Steven,</hi> but this, That <hi>he had taught that Jeſus of Nazareth ſhould change the Cuſtomes that Moſes had delivered them?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 6.14.</note> What was it that they accuſed <hi>Paul</hi> for;<note place="margin">Act. 16.21.</note> but this, that he taught <hi>Cuſtomes which were not lawfull for them to receive and obſerve being Romans,</hi> and ſo of another religion? Juſt as our adverſaries ſay againſt us; that wee teach a religion that it is not lawfull for them to receive, &amp;c. being Romans, Romiſh Catholikes. What was it that the ſhout was lifted up for the ſpace of two hours together; but this,<note place="margin">Act. 19.28.</note> 
                  <hi>Great is Diana of the Epheſians?</hi> What was it that <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid he was ſo exceedingly zealous about before his conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; but this,<note place="margin">Gal. 1.14.</note> 
                  <hi>about the tradition of his Fathers?</hi> What was it that St. <hi>Peter</hi> put the converted in mind<note place="margin">Pet. 1.18.</note>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:114709:61"/>of;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.2.</note> But this, that they <hi>were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed by the precious blood of Chriſt from their vaine converſation, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by tradition from their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi> If it be ſo hard a thing therefore to bring men out of an old Religion into a new one, and the world was ſo rooted and habituated in their vaine converſations receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by tradition from their Fathers; whence could a world ſo rooted and habituated therein, have beene brought unto the obedience of the Goſpel; but by the power of him that was raiſed from the dead? And ſo in the ſecond place, a world ſo captived under Satan.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="98" type="page">
               <p>Thirdly, whence not onely ſuch a world, but by <hi>ſuch twelve men,</hi> for number ſo few, but twelve men? whereas another whole world had been little enough to have ſent forth, to have ſubdued unto their Doctrine the preſent world; and for condition twelve ſo ſeemingly weake and impotent, and utterly unable for ſuch a buſines whereas twelve Angels even of the higheſt
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:114709:61"/>order, great in authority, mighty in power, charmfull and perſwaſive in ſpeech, and not ſuch twelve weake men as the Apoſtles, had been little enough for the buſines. Verily, he that wiſt not of him that was riſen from the dead, and had all power given unto him in Heaven and in earth, and ſo had ſent forth theſe twelve men into the world; with <hi>Ecce, ego vobiſcum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matt. 28.20.</note> 
                  <hi>I am with you to the end of the world;</hi> would have laughed at the conceit to have ſeene twelve ſuch ſilly men, ſo appointed as they were, With nothing but ſtaves in their hands and ſcrips by their ſides, to goe forth beginning at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and ſo on into the whole world to ſubdue it unto themſelves; as if twelve the ſillieſt here ſhould have a conceit to goe to <hi>Rome</hi> to perſwade there the Pope and all his Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalls, and all the Colledges of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits and Schools of Doctours and Covens of ſo many orders to leave all of them that Religion wherein they had been bred and brought up,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:114709:62"/>and whereout they ſuck no ſmall advantage, and to returne to their opinion: or as if twelve ſilly ſheep ſhould have a conceit to goe to the woods full of Wolves and Tygers and Bears and Lyons to perſwade them to leave off their wildneſs and ſavageneſs, and become tame and gentle and harmleſs as themſelves; theſe twelve ſilly ſheep, were they not more likely to be ſnapt up themſelves between the teeth of ſo many wild beaſts, then to do any good upon them? and theſe twelve ſilly men, were not they likely ſooner to be ſnapt up themſelves of the Romiſh Inquiſition, then to do any good upon that confirmed ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinated company? That the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles therefore, twelve ſilly men, like ſo many ſilly ſheep, were not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried preſently of ſo many Wolves, and Tygers, and Bears, and Hell-hounds, that they met with abroad in the world, but perſwaded many of them to leave their wild and wolviſh natures, and drew the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed obſtinated world out of all their old Religion to embrace their
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:114709:62"/>Doctrine; whence could it be but from the power of him that was ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen from the dead, from the power of him that ſaid, <hi>Lo, I am with you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ecce ego vobiſcum.</note> &amp;c? <hi>Who am I,</hi> ſaid Moſes, <hi>that I ſhould goe to Pharaoh, and that I ſhould bring forth the Children of Iſrael out of Egypt?</hi> Who I?<note place="margin">Exo. 3.11.</note> I but one, I but ſlow of ſpeech and ſlow of tongue, I that already have offended <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and yet more ſhall offend him now by this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to make him ſeeke my life; who am I, &amp;c? So, who were the Apoſtles? the Apoſtles but twelve in number, but ſlow of ſpeech and ſlow of tongue for any eloquence, and that by that buſines ſhould provoke and offend the whole world preſently to ſeeke their lives; who were they, that they ſhould goe and perſwade Kings and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, Oratours and Philo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ophers, Scribes and Phariſees, Wiſe and Fooliſh, Noble and Ignoble, bond and free Greeke and Barbarian; in a word, Parthians, Medes, Elami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and the inhabitants of all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:114709:63"/>under Heaven? What were they that they ſhould goe, and have any hope to perſwade theſe (ſetled upon the Lees of their own old ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions) unto the obedience of the Goſpel? if twelve men (ſayes <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>) unskilfull of warre, naked of armes,<note place="margin">Hom. 4 in 1 Cor.</note> weake in body, ſhould ſet upon a huge army of tall ſouldiers well appointed, and run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with their naked bodies in the thick of them, ſhould deale their blows ſo faſt, and ſo beſtirre them, that they ſhould kill ſome, wound others, lead others away Captive, vanquiſh all, and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves receive no harme, would not all ſay that this were a work Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine? What were the twelve ſilly Apoſtles but theſe twelve men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfull of warre, &amp;c? what was the whole world but a huge, huge army of tall ſouldiers well appointed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them? what was the run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of thoſe twelve men with naked bodies into the midſt of the army, but the venturing of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles upon the pikes point in the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:114709:63"/>midſt of the world up in arms againſt them? what was the beſtirring themſelves ſo of thoſe twelve men, killing ſome, &amp;c. but the beſtirring themſelves ſo of the twelve Apoſtles in the world, as to ſubdue a great part of it upon the field, and to foile all the reſt, that they could not withſtand them? what was the receiving no harm of thoſe twelve themſelves in the midſt of all that garboile, but the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing of the Apoſtles ſo long unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed amidſt all the uproare and garboile of the world againſt them? <hi>Having obtained help of God, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue unto this day</hi> (continue in ſpite of all the worlds being in an up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roare againſt me) <hi>witneſſing both to ſmall and great,</hi> &amp;c. And,<note place="margin">Act. 26.22.</note> 
                  <hi>We have this treaſure in earthen veſſels,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>that the excellency of the power may be of God and not of us.</hi> What was the Apoſtles ſubduing the world and caſting downe every high thing that exalted it ſelf againſt the knowledge of God, but the ſilly Rams horns making the high walls
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:114709:64"/>of <hi>Jericho</hi> fall downe flat!<note place="margin">Joſhua. 6.20.</note> or <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deons</hi> ſilly Barley cake tumbling in the hoſte of Midian and overturn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the tent?<note place="margin">Judges 7.13.</note> And therefore to put all together, whence but from the power of him that was riſen from the dead, ſending the power of the holy Ghoſt upon the Apoſtles and their labours, could ſuch a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, to ſuch a world by ſuch twelve (or thirteen men, to adde <hi>Paul</hi> to the dozen) have beene effectually preached? ſurely he that was ſet at the right hand of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had remembred what he had ſaid;<note place="margin">John 15.16.</note> 
                  <hi>I have choſen you and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned you, that you ſhould go and bring forth fruit, and that your fruit ſhould remaine.</hi> And this, this was that did the deed; elſe what hope that they ſhould have gone and brought forth ſuch fruit, in the converſion of the Gentiles, ſuch plentifull fruit, ſuch laſting fruit. Not without good cauſe, for one part of the myſtery of Godlineſs, is this,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.16.</note> 
                  <hi>God believed on in the world;</hi> not without good cauſe that <hi>Paul</hi>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:114709:64"/>calls the worke of the Gentiles-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion the opening of a doore,<note place="margin">Act. 14.27. 1 Cor. 16.9. 2 Cor. 2.12. Act. 12. <hi>Chryſ.</hi> Hom. 34. and 76. in Matt. Hom. 7. in 1 Cor.</note> if God had not miraculouſly opened this doore, as he made the Iron gate to open to <hi>Peter</hi> of its own accord, the Gentile had ſtood without for ever.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Whence had the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians and Converts ſuch extraordinary grace of holineſs of life, but from the power of him that was riſen from the dead, ſending the power of the holy ſanctifying ſpirit upon them?<note place="margin">Act. 2.</note> Conſider thoſe three thouſand firſt converted.<note place="margin">Act. 4.</note> And the five thouſand; Conſider their extraordinary <hi>piety, unity, commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity;</hi> Their extraordinary <hi>piety</hi> 'towards God teſtified by their zeale in religious exerciſes; <hi>They continued ſtedfaſtly in the Apoſtles Doctrine,</hi> &amp;c. Their extraordinary <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> or agreement among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, <hi>And all that believed were together,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> not ſo much in place (for three thouſand one place would hardly receive them) as in affection, <hi>they were of one heart and one Soul.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 4.32.</note>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:114709:65"/>Laſtly their extraordinary <hi>communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> for communion of all things to the mutuall help one of another, <hi>and had all things common,</hi> &amp;c. See but the backwardneſs now adays in theſe Chriſtian duties, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge their forwardneſs in the ſame to have been the very finger and worke of Gods ſpirit; They con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued <hi>ſtedfaſtly,</hi> or indefatigable in the Apoſtles Doctrine, &amp;c, we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps are but quarterly, or monthly, or fortnight men or women herein; or if weekly, then forenone people onely; or if ſo good as afternoone people too, yet our yawnings, our nods, yea, and perhaps our Naps too, argue our ſluggiſhneſs in theſe duties; but they continued indefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigable, &amp;c. Again, they, even the multitude of them, that believed (which is <hi>ſignanter</hi> ſpoken) <hi>ſignan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> that a multitude, and a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of raw converts ſhould be ſo; were ſo united and knit in one, that they had all as 'twere but one heart and one Soul; but one heart and one Soul to act and move ſo many,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:114709:65"/>many bodies; three thouſand Chap. 2. nay five thouſand Chap. 4. Whereas we run diviſion, ſo that it were a very wonder to ſee now but three or five men to be that which three, nay five thouſand men were then, even to have but one heart, and one Soul, laughing and weeping all together, nilling and willing all the ſame things; nay rather for five of us, our Saviours words, what if they proved true, that five ſhould be divided, three againſt two and two againſt three? but they, <hi>even the multitude of them that believed, being about five thouſand, were of one heart and of one Soul;</hi> Again, for outward fortunes, they had all things common, <hi>They that had goods and poſſeſſions ſold them;</hi> and they ſold them not to retaine the money in their own hands, to give a little as they liſted; but they <hi>laid it down at the Apoſtles feet,</hi> alienat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away the right of it from them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, to ſerve for the common ſtock wholly; and this they did when they could looke for no other
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:114709:66"/>but preſent perſecution: that money in their purſes in their flight, when they were perſecuted, would have done well. This they did alſo without the Apoſtles exhorting them thereto, as is intimated by the phraſe, <hi>laid it down</hi> at the Apoſtles feet; namely, the Apoſtles being unwilling to receive it, and plainlier expreſſed by that of <hi>Peter</hi> to <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias, While it remained, was it not thine own,</hi> &amp;c. This (Laſtly) they did, having (no doubt) ſome of them wives and children to take care for of their own: and were they thinke you without affection to their own that had ſuch affection to every Chriſtian?</p>
               <p>Let our own hearts now tell us, whether this that they did could well be any thing elſe but the very finger and worke of the ſpirit? this, that whereas the world huncheth to give a little of that they have, they gave all: whereas the world huncheth to give theſe little in time of peace, they gave their all when nothing but perſecution could be
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:114709:66"/>looked for; whereas the world not with all the exhortations that can be uſed, they without exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at all; whereas the world thinkes wife and children enough to hinder from giving a little, they thought it not enough to hinder from giving all, and yet had affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions better ordered indeed but as ſtrong for the life as the world could to wife and children. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps thou maiſt ſay, they had more zeale then wit; but take heed thou have not more wit then grace; when their zeale ſhall be rewarded in Heaven, take heed they wit be not puniſhed in Hell: Conſider therefore theſe three thouſand and five thouſand Chriſtians, and whence could they have this extraordinary grace of holineſs but from a Divine power, &amp;c. ſo rare and admirable was this their holy converſation, that it procured them grace with all the people; nay great grace;<note place="margin">Act. 2.47. and 4.33. and 5.13.</note> nay ſo great, that they magnified them; Conſider againe he writes in 1 Theſ. 1.3. <hi>remembring without
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:114709:67"/>ceaſing your work of faith and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of love,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſo that ye were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſamples to all that believe.</hi> Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der alſo what the very Pagans wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed concerning the old Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians extraordinary holineſs; <hi>Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> writes, that ſome Renegadoes, counterfeit Chriſtians, being exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined about the ſecret but ſacred conventicles of Chriſtians, could ſay no more then thus of them, That they uſed at ſet dayes to meet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore day, and there to ſing praiſes to Chriſt as God, and to bind them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with a holy vow not to doe any miſchiefe;<note place="margin">Sed ne fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, ne La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trocinia, ne adulteria committe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent; ne fidem falle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, ne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitum ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negarent; <hi>lib. 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Epiſ. 97.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>that they ſhould not commit any theft, or robbery, or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ultery; nor breake their word, nor withhold that which was committed to them to keepe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that very wretch <hi>Julian</hi> writes thus to a Paganiſh Biſhop; namely to ſtudy to promote the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganiſh Religion as the Chriſtian Religion was at firſt promoted, to wit, by holineſs of life, hoſpitality to ſtrangers, liberality to all, &amp;c. <hi>Turpe namque eſt,</hi> &amp;c. for it is a
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:114709:67"/>ſhame (ſayes he) that thoſe impious Galilaeans ſhould have enough for their own, and relieve the Jew,<note place="margin">Tert. 6.29.</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Pagan too, and we not relieve our own. Alſo,<note place="margin">Bonus Vir <hi>Cajus Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus,</hi> ſed tantum malus quòd Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</note> they uſed to ſay, <hi>ſuch an one was a good man, but onely bad in this, that he was a Chriſtian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Conſider laſtly, that the old Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in their very appeals to the Gentiles, were confident to ſtand upon the Chriſtians innocency;<note place="margin">Quis illic ſicarius? quis manti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularius? quis ſacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus aut corruptor?</note> 
                  <hi>what privie murtherer</hi> (or Aſſaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate) <hi>is there among Chriſtians? what Pick-purſe? what Sacrilegious perſon</hi> (or Church-robber?) <hi>what cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupter?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo much of the teſtimony of the Spirit; hereunto may be added the teſtimony of <hi>Joſephus</hi> a Jew,<note place="margin">John 15.26.</note> bearing witneſſe of his Reſurrection the third day,<note place="margin">Act. 5.32.</note> and appearing to his Diſciples.<note place="margin">Antiqu. 18.4.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, Whence had the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Martyrs and Confeſſors that extraordinary grace of ſufferings, but from the power of the holy Ghoſt? This wee cannot but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:114709:68"/>if we conſider the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſality, invincibility, patience and joy of their ſufferings;</p>
               <p>The <hi>univerſality,</hi> in that ſo many of all ſorts and conditions; as well of feeble women and tender chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, as men; as well of the rich, and thoſe that were brought up in all tenderneſs, and delicacies, as of the poore, and thoſe that were uſed to more hardſhips; as well of the wiſe and underſtanding, that would not have been cozened with a fable to have hazarded their lives, as of the ſilly and ignorant; in that ſo many of all ſorts are regiſtred Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs and Confeſſours; ſo many, that (by computation) the very Martyrs that were ſlaine for the name Chriſt, are thought to equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize for number, or exceed all the ſacrifices that were under the Law ſacrificed as types of Chriſt; and yet there was offered at once <hi>two and twenty thouſand oxen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">3 Kings 1.63.</note> 
                  <hi>and an hundred and twenty thouſand ſheep;</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, If we conſider the <hi>invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibility</hi> of their ſufferings; in that
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:114709:68"/>not all the variety of torments, not all the extremity of torments, not all the protractedneſs of torments, that the wit of man and the malice of man could deviſe (and what more ingenious then wit and malice put together) not all could overcome them, but invincibly they perſiſted againſt all; againſt ſuch torments, that it were enough to ſtrike hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour into the heart to heare them related; how their joynts were ſtretched upon the rack, drawne off one after another, how their bowels were ſcrued and twined out of their bodies, by little and little beginning at the Navill; how their fleſh was nipped and pulled away peece-meale with pincers, how their ſides were ſcraped till the very bare ribbs ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared with iron ſcallops or ſcra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers how under their nails (one of the ſenſibleſt places) they were peirced with ſharp needles run into the root of the nails, and the fleſh of the nails pickd out with little hooky inſtruments; how they were roſted, broiled on Gridirons, ſet in
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:114709:69"/>red hot iron chairs; and as for their throwing them down hard ſteep rocks to breake their necks, and their caſting them to wild beaſts, and their burning them at ſtakes, theſe gentle deaths were favours. If we conſider their invincibleneſs in all theſe, what ſhall we ſay but that it was the power of the holy Ghoſt upon them? the power of the holy Ghoſt upon that <hi>Blandina,</hi> that invincibly endured all torments from morning till night, and when her tormentors that ſucceſſively one after another were to inflict the torments, confeſſed at night they were quite tyred, ſhee invincible, was freſher to endure new tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments then they to inflict them.<note place="margin">Euſeb. 5.1.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Again, if we conſider the <hi>patience</hi> of their ſufferings, to take all thoſe torments not onely ſo invincibly, but ſo <hi>patiently;</hi> ſo patiently, in that <hi>(firſt)</hi> ſo willingly, when they might have been rid of their tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with thanks too, if they would but in two words have denied Chriſt; whereas perhaps there may
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:114709:69"/>be ſome very wretches that may harden themſelves in patience, but it is when they ſee there is no reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as traitours, <hi>Ravilliacks,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>(Secondly)</hi> So <hi>patiently,</hi> in that ſo meekly, ſo uncomplainingly, not complaining of the extremity, not crying out in that bitterneſs of their Soul, unſufferable, unſufferable, as meere fleſh and blood would have done; but ſo meekly and uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plainingly enduring all torments without any whining or whimping, as if they had ſuffered in other mens bodies, or their bodies had been bodies of marble, or their fleſh of braſſe. This <hi>patience</hi> is above their former invincibleneſs; invincible one may be through reſolution, and yet a little impatient when extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity is upon them through frailty; but to be not only ſo invincible, but ſo patient too, whence this but from the power of the holy Ghoſt upon them?</p>
               <p>Laſtly, if wee conſider the <hi>joy of their ſufferings,</hi> not onely ſo pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently, but ſo <hi>joyfully</hi> to take their
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:114709:70"/>ſufferings; <hi>ye became</hi> (ſayes the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle,) <hi>followers of us &amp; of the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rd,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 1.6.</note> 
                  <hi>having received the word in much affliction with joy of the holy Ghoſt;</hi> And St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaking of the ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of Chriſtians, and fiery triall of their faith, what teſtimony gives he them? <hi>ſcil.</hi> this; that <hi>through their faith, though they ſaw not, yet believing they rejoyced with joy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable and full of glory.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.8.</note> And they that read Eccleſiaſtical hiſtory, know that the Martyrs and Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours went ſo joyfully to their ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, that divers conſidering it were converted all wondred, their adverſaries that tormented them fretted; fretted and were full of greife to ſee them ſo full of joy, to ſee them goe to the ſtake, as if it had been but to a bonefire to be merry; alſo to ſee them burne in the flames as if they had been but beaking in the ſun; to ſee them ſtretching on the rack, as if they had been ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves on their beds of Ivory; to ſee them that all the reſt of their life through a Chriſtian gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:114709:70"/>and modeſty looked like mourners, ſee them now have ſuch cheerfull countenances, as if nothing but mirth and joy ſat in their faces, &amp;c. whence therefore had the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Confeſſours and Martyrs this extraordinary grace of ſufferings, to ſuffer ſo <hi>univerſally,</hi> ſo <hi>invincibly,</hi> ſo <hi>patiently,</hi> ſo <hi>joyfully,</hi> but from the power of the holy Ghoſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> Uſe Firſt, If their be ſuch evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of Chriſts Reſurrection, then this may let us ſee the great <hi>neceſſity of Chriſtian faith;</hi> how neceſſary it is to believe as we believe; how can I but believe that which the ſufferings of ſo many Martyrs and Confeſſours, the lives of ſo many Saints, the powerfull converſion of ſo many Gentiles, the ſtrangeneſs of ſo many miracles; the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likeneſs for extraordinary graces in the firſt preachers, the impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs of thoſe eye-witneſſes their being either deceivers or deceived, the harmony alſo and conſent of the old Teſtament, the very record of the Jews; how can I but believe that which is witneſſed unto by all
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:114709:71"/>theſe? If I will needs yet let in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity lurke in my heart, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things have I, may juſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne me? <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets that foretold theſe things ſhall condemne me; thoſe eye-witneſſes that witneſſed his Reſurrection, which if wilfully I ſhut not mine own eyes, muſt needs appeare to me could neither be deceivers nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, ſhall condemne me; thoſe firſt preachers that could not have their extraordinary grace but from the power of him that was riſen from the dead, ſhall condemne me; thoſe ſtrange miracles, that ſtrange converſion of the Gentiles, that ſtrange ſanctity and holineſs of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts, that ſtrange ſuffering of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, that could none of them have been but by the power of him that was riſen from the dead, ſhall all condemne me; if I believe not now the Goſpel, how juſtly am I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned!</p>
               <p>Wee are all ready in reading the ſtory of the old Teſtament, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the Jew, that he ſhould be in
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:114709:71"/>many things ſo ſtubborne, and unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving, notwithſtanding ſuch mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt declaration of Gods preſence among them: but if all things were well caſt up, wee ſhall find that we have more reaſon ten to one to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve under the Goſpel, then they had under the Law; and if an infidel-Jew may well go to Hell, an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del-Chriſtian deſerves to ſinke far the lower there; An infidel Jew, if he believed not, it was ſtill a thing to come that he believed not; the infidell Chriſtian a thing paſt: Chriſts Reſurrection, an infidel-Jew had no argument almoſt to confirme his beliefe, but the conſideration of a little ſtrange miraculous working; the infidell-Chriſtan hath argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments above all miracles, and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over miracles above all <hi>Moſes</hi> his miracles; and therefore let us by the evidences of Chriſts Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and ſo conſequently of the whole Goſpel, for the Reſurrection is the ſeale, and warrant, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement of all, therefore in their choice of a twelfth, they name no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:114709:72"/>thing but onely <hi>to be a witneſſe of the Reſurrection;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 1.22.</note> let us hereby charme and conjure out of our hearts all infidelity, and let us eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh our ſelves in our moſt holy faith; this, how neceſſary it is, not onely to believe but alſo to ſee the neceſſity of our beliefe, let two places teach you;<note place="margin">Luke 1.4. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>(ſcil) That thou maiſt know the certainty of thoſe things wherein thou haſt been inſtructed;</hi> And, <hi>Theſe things have I written to you that believe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 John 5.13.</note> 
                  <hi>that ye may know that ye have eternal life;</hi> If it had not been a neceſſary thing, and of much uſe to labour to ſee the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Chriſtian faith, the one would not have rendered it for a reaſon in the beginning of his Goſpel, why he writ his Goſpel; and the other in the end of his Epiſtle why he writ his Epiſtle; and therefore <hi>(firſt)</hi> if there be ſuch evidences, conſider the neceſſity of Chriſtian faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, If there be ſuch evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of Chriſts Reſurrection, let us ſee the <hi>neceſſity of Chriſtian life;</hi>
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:114709:72"/>if there be ſuch compelling argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to perſwade me to ſee the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of <hi>Chriſtian faith</hi> then what remains but that in the next place I ſhould thinke of the neceſſity of <hi>Chriſtian life?</hi> How dare I live as an Atheiſt, if I cannot but profeſſe and believe as a Chriſtian? how dare I caſt away my commandements, if I cannot but embrace my creed? how dare I make ſo little of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs of the Goſpel, if I cannot but acknowledge the truth of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel? Verily, this is the condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of many: that <hi>Chriſtian faith</hi> being ſo <hi>cleare, Chriſtian life</hi> is ſo <hi>bad; This is the condemnation, that light is come into the world</hi> (ſc. not light hid under a cloud or under a buſhel,<note place="margin">John 3.19.</note> but light appearing to be light) <hi>yet men love darkneſs rather then light.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 15.24.</note> And <hi>If I had not done among them the works which none other did, they had not had ſin,</hi> &amp;c. And, <hi>When the Spirit is come, he will reprove the world of ſin,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 1.7.</note> 
                  <hi>becauſe they believe not on mee;</hi> And, <hi>They ſhall receive the reward of unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:114709:73"/>as they that count it pleaſure to riot in the day-time.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.13.</note> When the truth of the Goſpel is ſo cleare, that if indeed there were any cauſe why thou mighteſt doubt of the truth of the Goſpel, if the mouth of all infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity were not ſufficiently ſtopt, if Gods truth and teſtimonies were not very ſure,<note place="margin">Pſal. 93.3. <hi>Credibilia factanimis.</hi>
                  </note> then ſom reaſon there might be of thy hankering and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering and back-hanging in the courſe of a godly life: but if the truth of the Goſpel be ſo plaine, beware of hardning thy heart a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the holineſs of the Goſpel; He whom the <hi>truth</hi> of the Goſpel <hi>convicts,</hi> the <hi>holineſs</hi> of the Goſpel being neglected ſhall <hi>confound; The wrath of God</hi> (ſayes the Apoſtle) <hi>is revealed againſt all ungodlineſs and unrighteouſneſs of men,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 1.20.</note> 
                  <hi>who hold the truth in unrighteouſneſs;</hi> even the truth ſhewing it ſelf onely in the evidence of <hi>nature;</hi> much more in the evidence of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> muſt the wrath of God needs be revealed, &amp;c. Marke the connexion of the Pſalmiſt; <hi>Thy teſtimonies are very
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:114709:73"/>ſure;</hi> and what then? <hi>Holineſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes thy houſe for ever.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 93.5.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Well, I will wind up this with the grave ſpeech of that good man <hi>Mirandula,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Magna pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectò inſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> It is (ſayes he) a great madneſs not to believe the Goſpel, the truth whereof ſo many things evidently ſpeake and proclaime, the ſufferings of the Martyrs, &amp;c. but it is a farre greater madneſs if any doubt not of the truth of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, yet ſo to live as if he doubted not of the falſeneſs of the Goſpel; what is this but to ſee Hell, and yet to leap into it? to ſee Heaven and yet not to care for falling from it? what is it (in a word but to run ful) butt againſt God, with eyes wide open? and what is madneſs if this be not? ſurely ſuch ſacred majeſty will not be rubbed and jurred upon by profaneneſs that is blind, but it ſhal beare the puniſhment; for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſs, to run full butt againſt God with eyes wide open, what puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment then may be looked for? this is far worſe then <hi>Balaams</hi> carriage, he would but have gone upon the
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:114709:74"/>Angel of the Lord ſtanding in his way, with a ſword drawn in his hand, and not ſeeing the Angel nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: But to ſee God-ſtanding in the way to ſtop the ſinner, and the ſinner to ſay, yonder he ſtands; yonder, that would ſtop me in my unlawfull gaine, ſtop me in my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull pleaſure, ſtop me in my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane courſe of life, yonder he ſtands, but yet have at him; what madneſs is this! When the pitcher flyes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the wall and breaks not, when a man runs his head full butt againſt a pillar and his brains daſh not out, then ſhal he run thus ful butt againſt God and his known ordinances and ſhatter not, periſh not, not utterly be confounded body and ſoul for ever. And therefore this alſo may let us ſee the great neceſſity of <hi>Chriſtian life:</hi> conſider thoſe things that ſhew the neceſſity of Chriſtian faith, and be an Atheiſt if thou canſt; conſider the neceſſity of Chriſtian faith, and be a profane wretch if thou dareſt; ſee Hell and leap into it, ſee Heaven and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:114709:74"/>it, ſee God in thy way and run full butt upon him with eyes wide open;<note place="margin">Heb. 2.3.</note> 
                  <hi>How ſhall we eſcape if we neglect ſo great Salvation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> Thirdly, If there be ſuch evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of Chriſts Reſurrection, then we may know how to give a reaſon of the <hi>hope</hi> that is in us;<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.15.</note> 
                  <hi>Be ready alwayes to give an anſwer to every man that asketh you a reaſon of the hope that is in you;</hi> not to every one that asketh you a reaſon of any point of Chriſtian Doctrine, or Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-bearing; that is too much for every Chriſtian to doe: but every Chriſtian ſhould be able to give a reaſon of the <hi>Chriſtian hope</hi> that is in him; now the hope of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian is to be ſaved by Chriſt the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour riſen from the dead, as you have it;<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed be the God and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who hath begotten us again to a lively hope, by the Reſurrection of Chriſt from the dead;</hi> he therefore that can give a reaſon of Chriſts Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection from the dead; gives good reaſon of his Chriſtian hope, he
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:114709:75"/>hath good reaſon to truſt him for a Saviour, that hath ſaved himſelfe, and to believe his Doctrine that God hath ſealed the truth of it, with raiſing the Prophet that taught it from the dead. Marke the Apoſtle how he toucheth upon theſe three very ſame reaſons here for the eſtabliſhing us in our lively hope by the Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt from the dead: whereupon we have inſiſted for the proofe of the Reſurrection;<note place="margin">verſe 10.</note> Firſt, upon the teſtimony of the old Teſtament, <hi>Of which Salvation the Prophets have enquired,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 12.</note> &amp;c. Secondly, upon the teſtimony of the eye-witneſſes; <hi>which are now reported unto you,</hi> &amp;c. Thirdly, by the teſtimony of the Spirit, <hi>which the holy Ghoſt ſent down from Heaven,</hi> &amp;c. and what now follows, but that therefore we have good reaſon to ſtand firme in our hope?<note place="margin">verſe 13.</note> 
                  <hi>wherefore gird up the loyns of your mind, be ſober and hope to the end;</hi> hope unto the end, and let neither the fury of the unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving world perſecuting you, nor the
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:114709:75"/>fleeres and jeeres of the profane world flouting you, be able to daſh you in your hope; but hope to the end; for now that you know that Chriſt muſt needs be riſen from the dead, you know how to give an anſwer to any one that ſhall aske a reaſon of the hope that is in you;<note place="margin">Act. 26.</note> Paul in his <hi>Apology</hi> toucheth much upon the ſame reaſons;</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>4</label> Fourthly, if there be ſuch evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of Chriſts Reſurrection; then it is evident that Chriſt was the right <hi>Meſſias,</hi> for if he had been an impoſtor and falſe Prophet, neither could he have raiſed up him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe being but a meere man, nor would God have raiſed him up being but a meer impoſtor; nor can it be ſaid that the Divell might raiſe up his falſe Prophet, for he that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>give ſight to one borne blind,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 9.</note> can much leſſe give life to one ſtark dead; he cannot revive all the ſenſes and the whole man, that cannot ſo much as revive one ſenſe, the ſight: if the Divell could raiſe up a dead man to life; he might as well make
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:114709:76"/>a man of dead matter; It will be Gods ſole priviledge for ever to be a God that raiſeth up the dead;<note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.9.</note> if therefore there be ſuch evidences of his Reſurrection, this is thought ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument enough by our Saviour and the Apoſtles to prove him to be the right Meſſias; this Reſurrection from the dead: So when they cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for a ſigne from our Saviour to prove him that he was the right Meſſias, as he pretended, he inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth in his Reſurrection, as ſigne enough alone to convince them that he was the Meſſias;<note place="margin">Matt. 12.38.39.</note> 
                  <hi>Maſter, we would ſee a ſigne,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>no ſigne but the ſigne of the Prophet Jonas, as he was three dayes and three nights in the Whales belly, ſo ſhall the ſon of man be three dayes,</hi> &amp;c. So when the Jews (ſeeing him take upon himſelfe the office of the Meſſias) asked him what ſigne he ſhowed, the ſigne he inſtanceth in was onely this; <hi>Deſtroy this Temple, and I will raiſe it up in three dayes;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 2.19.</note> 
                  <hi>ſo when yee have lift up the ſon of man</hi> (ſc. crucified him,<note place="margin">John 8.28.</note> and he be raiſed
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:114709:76"/>again from the dead) <hi>then ſhall yee know that I am be.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 2.36.</note> So St. Peter <hi>Therefore</hi> (becauſe he hath raiſed him from the dead) <hi>let all the houſe of Iſrael know that God hath made that ſame Jeſus both Lord and Chriſt;</hi> ſo St. Paul,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Declared to be the ſon of God by the Reſurrection from the dead;</hi> and ſo undoubted an argument is this, that the Jews ſaw they muſt either deny the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, or neceſſarily grant that he was the Meſſias; and therefore they tooke the beſt way they could for hindering any ſuppoſedneſs of it, confeſſing that if the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction was once probably blazed abroad, the laſt errour would be worſe then the firſt.<note place="margin">Matt. 27.64. and 42.</note> 
                  <hi>Come downe now from the croſſe, and wee will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,</hi> ſaid the chiefe Prieſts and elders; Come up from the dead, and wee will believe; they could not but have confeſſed this to have been an argument much ſtronger, and therefore Chriſt was the right Meſſias.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>5</label> Fifthly, If Chriſt be riſen from
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:114709:77"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:114709:77"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:114709:78"/>the dead, then he will undoubtedly alſo come to judgment; for why roſe he from the dead but <hi>to receive all power in heaven and in earth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matt. 28.18.</note> and to have every knee bow unto him?<note place="margin">Phil. 2.10.</note> And why received he this power but to execute it, and make every knee bow unto him? and where (as yet) appears this execution, when there are ſo many ſtiffe-knees yet, that will not bow unto him, I meane diſobedient ones, that will not obey him? and therefore cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly he will come one day to judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when he ſhall make all them that will not bend now, breake; that will not bow now under his mercy, bow then under his juſtice; that will not now kiſſe the top of his golden Scepter reached out in grace and loving kindneſs, be cruſhed by that Scepter-bruiſing them in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure; ſee the connexion which Scripture uſually makes, uſually joyning or ſubjoyning judgment to the mention of the Reſurrection; <hi>him hath God raiſed up the third day,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 10.40.42.</note> &amp;c. and what then? <hi>and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:114709:78"/>us to preach unto the people,</hi> &amp;c. ſo Act. 17.30.31. <hi>but now he commandeth all men every where to repent, becauſe he hath appointed a day in which he will judge the world by him whom he hath raiſed from the dead:</hi> ſo 1 Theſ. 1.10. <hi>and to wait for his Son from Heaven;</hi> and why? what aſſurance for it? why the aſſurance of his Reſurrection, <hi>whom he hath raiſed from the dead;</hi> there is the aſſurance; If therefore Chriſt be riſen from the dead, he will certainly alſo come to judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he will not ſuffer the world alwayes to run ſo upon wheels, to be ſo diſorderly and full of confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, man rebelling againſt his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, the godly trampled under foot by the wicked, ſervants riding on horſeback and Princes going a foot, the tayl ſtanding where the head ſhould be, &amp;c. he will not alwayes ſuffer this confuſion, but thoſe times of the reſtitution of all things ſhall come,<note place="margin">Act. 3.21.</note> when every thing ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to its own place, when all gimmels ſhall be right, when all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:114709:79"/>and confuſion ſhall flee away, when all things that offend ſhall be taken out of his Kingdome;</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>6</label> Sixthly, If Chriſt be riſen from the dead, then ſin is conquered, for the ſting of death is ſin: ſo long therefore as death had this deadly ſting in it, death could not have been conquered by any ſon of <hi>Adam,</hi> every ſon of <hi>Adam</hi> being obnoxious to death by vertue of <hi>morte morieris,</hi> thou ſhalt die the death, though he had no ſin in him, actuall or originall, but onely the imputation of <hi>Adams</hi> diſobedience; that Chriſt therefore, a ſon of <hi>Adam</hi> roſe victoriouſly from the dead, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoriouſly, never to returne thither again,<note place="margin">Act. 13.34.</note> or death to have no more dominion over him;<note place="margin">Rom. 6.9.</note> (for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>Lazarus</hi> and others were rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from the dead, but it was to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne thither again;) it muſt needs be, that ſin was conquered by him; See the Scripture making this uſe of Chriſts Reſurrection, the foil and conqueſt of ſin;<note place="margin">Act. 13.38.</note> ſo <hi>Paul</hi> after he had urged and proved Chriſts Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection;
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:114709:79"/>what infers he there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon? <hi>Bee it known unto you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that through this man is preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto you forgiveneſs of ſins;</hi> ſo, <hi>he was delivered for our ſins, and was raiſed again for our Juſtification;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 4.25.</note> our Juſtification from ſin is eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly given to his Reſurrection, becauſe by his Reſurrection he did Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate and make it plaine, that ſin was conquered; his death would have done us no good, if it had been poſſible that he could have beene holden by the power of death; ſo, <hi>Who is he that condemneth?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.34.</note> 
                  <hi>it is Chriſt that dyed, yea rather that is riſen again;</hi> what is the reaſon of this correction, of this <hi>yea rather,</hi> &amp;c? was not Chriſts dying enough to free us from any condemning by ſin? yes; but it was, becauſe it was the death of him that had power alſo to riſe again, &amp;c. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the redemption of us from our ſin, appeared eſpeciall in his power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Reſurrection. So in the preſent Chapter, <hi>If Chriſt be not riſen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.17.</note> 
                  <hi>then are we yet in our ſins;</hi> imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:114709:80"/>that his Reſurrection is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of ſin; we have therefore what to anſwer all the infernall powers of Hell, challenging us of ſin, even to anſwer them with the Apoſtle, <hi>Who is he that condemneth? it is Chriſt that dyed, yea rather that is riſen again;</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>7</label> Seventhly, If Chriſt be riſen from the dead, then Piety and Religion comfort your ſelves; that hope is in a ſtrong redeemer, and one that can deliver you out of the hand of all your enemies; he that was too hard for death, will be too hard for any of your enemies; he hath ſlaine the great Goliah, and is he not able then to put any weaker Philiſtim to flight for you? he hath broken the barres of death, and is he not able to breake the barres and gates of all the other enemies? be comforted therefore againſt all feare and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour. Not a haire of your heads can periſh without his providence; and if it be his providence, it is no great matter though yee loſe your heads too; they that can take your
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:114709:80"/>heads from off your ſhoulders can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not take your crownes from of your heads; they may tumble your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies into the grave, they cannot ſeale the graves mouth upon them. Well ſaid St. <hi>Paul</hi> in comfort a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all his enemies and all his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions;<note place="margin">2 Timo. 1.10. and 12.</note> 
                  <hi>I know whom I have tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted</hi> (ſc. him that being riſen from the dead hath aboliſhed death;) <hi>and I am perſwaded that he is able to keepe that which I have committed unto him againſt that day;</hi> If Chriſt therefore be riſen, yee know whom yee truſt, even him that being raiſed from the dead, hath aboliſhed death, and is able to keepe that which you commit unto him againſt that day:</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>8</label> Eighthly, If Chriſt be riſen from the dead, then profaneneſs and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion beware your ſelves? your diſobedience is againſt as ſtrong a revenger, and one that is of as great power to confound his foes, as to ſave his ſervants. Their terrified hearts knew this,<note place="margin">Act. 2.36.37.</note> who no ſooner by St. <hi>Peters</hi> Sermon were they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of the Reſurrection, and
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:114709:81"/>that God had made that ſame Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus whom they crucified <hi>both Lord and Chriſt,</hi> but preſently they <hi>were pricked in their hearts, and ſaid unto Peter and the reſt, men and brethren, what ſhall wee doe?</hi> It made their hearts pant to thinke they had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended him, that now being riſen from the dead was made both Lord and Chriſt, and ſo able to take what terrible revenge he would of them. Conſider what is written in Matt. 21.44. There our Saviour bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out the 118. Pſal. (a Pſalme of the Reſurrection) cites this text; <hi>The ſtone which the builders refuſed, is become the head ſtone of the Corner;</hi> he adds, that <hi>whoſoever ſhall fall on this ſtone</hi> (through diſobedience offend, and ſtumble againſt it) <hi>ſhall be broken</hi> (it ſhall worke commonly his rume and confuſion for this world) <hi>but on whom ſoever it ſhall fall, it ſhall grind him to powder;</hi> on whom ſoever Chriſt at his ſecond coming ſhall with all the weight and might and vehemency of indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation fall, he ſhall then make pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:114709:81"/>and meere miſh-maſh of him:<note place="margin">Comparate vos cum Judaeis; illi contempſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentem in ligno; vos contemnitis ſedentem in coelo. <hi>Aug. de verbis Domini 45.</hi>
                  </note> If therefore Chriſt be riſen, you now ſpeake not a word nor doe a deed againſt the ſon of man, but againſt him that is declared to be the Son of God. Compare your felves with the Jews; they contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him when he hung upon the croſſe, you contemne him, when he ſits in Heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſ. </seg>2</label> Second <hi>Obſervation,</hi> That Chriſt is not onely riſen, but riſen as the firſt fruits to ſanctify and aſcertiane our Reſurrection; as the firſt fruits under the law being offered to God, were for the ſanctifying and procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a bleſſing upon the whole har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt: now this, that Chriſt is riſen as the firſt fruits, by his Reſurrection to ſanctifie and warrant our Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, divers things confirme it:</p>
               <p>Firſt, The example of thoſe that he actually brought with him from the dead when himſelfe roſe;<note place="margin">Matt. 27.52.53.</note> And the graves were opened, and many bodies of Saints which ſlept, aroſe; this little raſt before hand ſhowes what his Reſurrection ſhall be
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:114709:82"/>powerfull unto hereafter, even unto the raiſing of the dead bodies of the Saints that ſleepe; he ſet but two or three priſoners free, but the goale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delivery of all his he will performe hereafter: as he is powerfull to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute ſo he is wiſe not to precipitate and haſten counſels; but ſtay the fulneſs of time.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The vertue of his life and Reſurrection to revive us, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe ſpeeches of himſelfe ſhow; as that; <hi>As the living Father hath ſent me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 6.57.</note> 
                  <hi>and I live by the Father, ſo he that eateth me, even he ſhall live by me;</hi> live by me, ſo that I will raiſe him up at the laſt day, as <hi>foure times</hi> in that Chapter he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peats that phraſe. Againe, that ſpeech to <hi>Martha</hi> talking with him about her brother <hi>Lazarus</hi> his death, <hi>I am the Reſurrection and the life,</hi> &amp;c. Alſo that; <hi>Now is the bour come that the Son of man ſhould be glorified;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 11.25.</note> 
                  <hi>verily verily,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 12.23.</note> 
                  <hi>except a corn of wheat fall into the ground and dye, it abideth alone; but if it dye, it bringeth forth much fruit.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:114709:82"/>
               <p>Thirdly, The vertue of his life and Reſurrection to revive us, two ſpeciall appellations of his in Scirip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhow, namely the appellation of an <hi>Head,</hi> and the appellation of a <hi>Captaine;</hi> of a <hi>head,</hi> he being as a head unto his Church, and the Church the very body and members of him their head; if the body and members ſhall not be revived, there is no life in the very head it ſelfe: the head would derive life unto the body: hence from this union be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the head and members, are we ſaid to be already quickned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with him, raiſed together with him,<note place="margin">Eph. 2.5.</note> nay ſet down together with him in heavenly places;<note place="margin">Col. 2.12.</note> The other appellation is of a <hi>Captaine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> in that he is called the Captaine of life; <hi>yee killed the Captaine of life whom God had raiſed from the dead,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 3.15.</note> &amp;c. <hi>It became him for whom are all things,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 2.10.</note> 
                  <hi>to make the Captaine of their Salvation perfect through ſufferings;</hi> if <hi>Jeſus</hi> therefore be a Captain of life, and Salvation, he is not onely to ſave himſelf, but his Companies alſo
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:114709:83"/>that follow his colours; he is not a Captaine of life and Salvation, but of death and dectruction, that lets his company periſh in the field, though himſelfe come ſafe off with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any hurt.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, So enfolded one in the othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, is Chriſts Reſurrection and our Reſurrection, that the one is made to imply the other; ſo when the Apoſtle preached eſpecially Chriſts Reſurrection, yet the Prieſts and Sadduces tooke it ſo as preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Reſurrection through him; <hi>As they ſpake unto the people,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 4.1.2.</note> 
                  <hi>the prieſts,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>came in upon them, being greived that they preached through Jeſus the Reſurrection of the dead;</hi> So St. <hi>Paul</hi> in his Apology before the Phariſees and the Sadduces, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of making his Apology for Chriſts Reſurrection, turnes it into the generall, about our Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as indeed the one enfolding the other, ſo he might ſet the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee and Sadducee together by the ears, that ſo while the Wolves fight the Lambe might eſcape;<note place="margin">Act. 23.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Men
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:114709:83"/>and brethren, I am a Phariſee, of the hope and Reſurrection of the dead,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, To name no more autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, conſider the very next verſe of my text, and there you have Chriſt made the author of life and Reſurrection, as <hi>Adam</hi> of death; <hi>for ſince by man came death, by man came alſo the Reſurrection of the dead;</hi> And in the five and fortieth verſe you have another compariſon, that as the <hi>firſt Adam</hi> was made a living Soul, <hi>ſc.</hi> to become the fountaine of naturall life to all his poſterity; So the <hi>ſecond Adam</hi> (Chriſt) was made a quickning ſpirit; <hi>ſc.</hi> to become the fountaine of ſpirituall or Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly life to all his; <hi>The firſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam was made a living Soul, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend Adam was made a quickning ſpirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now before we come to the Uſes, a queſtion or two is not unſeaſonable to be made and anſwered;</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>1</label> Firſt, How Chriſt is the <hi>firſt fruits</hi> of all that ſlept;<note place="margin">1 King. 17.</note> ſeeing the widow of <hi>Sareptaes</hi> ſon was raiſed to life by <hi>Elias;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Kings 4.</note> and the Shunamites
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:114709:84"/>ſon, and a dead man by touch of <hi>Eliſha'es</hi> bones;<note place="margin">2 Kings 13.</note> and three by our Saviour himſelfe in his life time, ſc. <hi>Jairus</hi> his daughter in the cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber uncarried out; the widows one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſon upon the biere carried out at the gates of the City; and <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus</hi> having been four dayes in the grave, how therefore was Chriſt the <hi>firſt fruits,</hi> ſeeing theſe, and thoſe alſo, as it may ſeeme <hi>Matt.</hi> 27.52. were raiſed before him?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>1</label> For Anſwer, Obſerve firſt, That for all them that were raiſed to life, except perhaps thoſe <hi>Matt.</hi> 27. there was no proper Reſurrection, not ſuch a Reſurrection as we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe in our Creeds, not ſuch a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection as that;<note place="margin">Matt. 22.30.</note> 
                  <hi>In the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction they neither marry not are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in marriage, but are as the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels in Heaven;</hi> not a Reſurrection to a ſtate of immortality, but onely to the ſtate of their former naturall life, ſubject to death again: But as for our Saviours Reſurrection, he roſe ſo as now no more to returne to corruption;<note place="margin">Act. 13.37.</note> and death now to
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:114709:84"/>have no more dominion over him;<note place="margin">Rom. 6.9.</note> and as himſelfe ſaith, Rev. 1.18. now to be alive for evermore; <hi>I am he that liveth and was dead; and behold I am alive for evermore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>2</label> Secondly, For thoſe Matt. 27. either they roſe not till after Chriſts Reſurrection, as moſt thinke, ſo that the graves indeed opened at his death, but the dead bodies aroſe not till after Chriſts Reſurrection; <hi>And the graves were opened,</hi> &amp;c. ſc. thoſe there abouts in Mount-Calvary; or elſe if they roſe before his Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, then they roſe either upon diſpenſation onely for a time, to lay down their bodies again; or if to retaine their bodies for ever as glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious bodies, then Chriſts Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction was in order of nature, though not of time, before theirs, becauſe through the power and vertue of his Reſurrection they were raiſed; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as he is ſaid in the Councell and foreknowledge of God, to be a Lambe ſlaine from the foundation of the world, and therefore nothing hinders but that Chriſt was the firſt
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:114709:85"/>fruits; becauſe all that roſe before Chriſt, either roſe onely to a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall life; or if not, yet onely upon diſpenſation for a time, to lay down their bodies again; or if to retaine their bodies for ever, yet by the power and vertue of Chriſts Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection preconceived in Gods coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, as the fountaine and cauſe of their life and Reſurrection. And ſo wee may ſee,<note place="margin">Act. 26.23.</note> how Chriſt was to be the firſt that ſhould riſe from the dead; and here, the firſt fruits of them that ſlept, and the firſt borne from the dead;<note place="margin">Col. 1.18.</note> becauſe he roſe onely by his own power; <hi>I have power to lay it down,</hi> &amp;c. and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe never to return to corruption again.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>2</label> A ſecond queſtion is about the wicked, whether and how they are to be raiſed, ſeeing Chriſt cannot be ſaid to be their firſt fruits? whether and how therefore are they to be raiſed, whoſe Reſurrections are not hallowed and conſecrate in Chriſt;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.22.</note> in whom are all to be made alive?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>1</label> Firſt, <hi>That</hi> they ſhall riſe, there
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:114709:85"/>is no queſtion;<note place="margin">John 5.28 29.</note> 
                  <hi>The houre is coming in the which all that are in the graves ſhall heare his voice and ſhall come forth,</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">Act. 24.15.</note> 
                  <hi>and have hope to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, which they themſelves alſo allow that there ſhall be a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the dead, both of the juſt and of the unjuſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>2</label> Now ſecondly, <hi>How</hi> they ſhall be raiſed, whether in and by Chriſts Reſurrection or no? For this we are to know, that Chriſt by his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection was made Lord and onely Potentate of every creature,<note place="margin">Act. 2.36.</note> and therefore received power over quick and dead,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.11.</note> that he might be able to bring again from the dead all the wicked and diſobedient, as their judge to puniſh them; and all his own, as their Saviour to glorify them. Wherefore by Chriſts Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection both the wicked and the godly ſhall be raiſed; but the <hi>wicked,</hi> as the members of Satan onely to be damned, the <hi>godly,</hi> as members of his own body to be ſaved: The wicked by a power upon them onely from without;
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:114709:86"/>the godly by a power upon them from within, inhaerent in them, as his own members; as the head by an inward influence quickens the body: whereas the wicked ſhall be quickned by an outward influence onely upon them, as the ſun by an outward influence upon putrified ſlimy matter, animates and quickens frogs and toads; and therefore thoſe that he quickens by that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward influence, he ſhall make glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious like himſelfe; whereas thoſe that he quickens by an outward in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence only, ſhal not participate of his glory: like as thoſe creatures which the ſun quickens, though the ſun be a glorious body, yet they are not ſo, but filthy, abominable, wretched creatures, frogs, toads, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Well then for the <hi>cauſe</hi> of our Reſurrections, conſider firſt a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall judiciall cauſe; <hi>ſc.</hi> the <hi>juſtice of God,</hi> requiring that we ſhould all receive in our bodies, according to that which we have done in our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and therefore that we ſhould be raiſed again. And ſecondly a phyſical effecting cauſe, ſc. the
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:114709:86"/>
                  <hi>Lordly ſoveraigne power of Chriſt</hi> ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen from the dead, effecting the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the wicked as their judge, to make them comformable in torments to the Divell their head; and effecting the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the godly as their Saviour, to make them comformable in glory to himſelfe their head; and of theſe he is onely ſaid to be the <hi>firſt fruits,</hi> becauſe he ſhall onely hallow and dedicate theſe unto God in a glorious Reſurrection like unto his owne, bringing the whole harveſt of them without loſing one eare, into the ſame barne and Heavenly repoſitory; whereunto he the firſt fruits is already come. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore where it is ſaid here, that <hi>all ſhal be made alive in Chriſt;</hi> it is meant onely of his own members, that by an inward quickning influence upon them from him their head, ſhall be revived to the ſame glorious kind of life with himſelfe,<note place="margin">Matt. 25.46. Rom. 6.23. and 8.13.</note> which indeed is onely in Scripture phraſe the proper life, and the other but an eternall living death; And that
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:114709:87"/>theſe are onely meant, the next verſe ſhowes, where theſe all that are to be made alive in Chriſt, are called Chriſts; but for the wicked they are none of his, he owns them not, they are the limbs of the Divell, and none of his members.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
                  </label> Firſt, If Chriſt be riſen <hi>as the firſt fruits</hi> to enſure the glorious Reſurrection of his, then let this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh every one of us, as we deſire to be made partakers of this glorious Reſurrection, ſo to endeavour to belong unto theſe firſt fruits, <hi>ſc.</hi> to Chriſt; the firſt fruits doe not bleſſe the tares, and cockell and darnell, and all filthy weeds that grow among the Corne, but onely the good Corne; If we would be bleſſed therefore in Chriſt, the firſt fruits, let us not be tares, &amp;c. in Gods field, the Church; but let us be good Corne; otherwiſe the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable will read us our deſtinies; <hi>Gather together the tares, and bind them in bundles to burne them;</hi> in bundles to burne them, there is the deſtiny of the tares;<note place="margin">Matt. 13.30.</note> 
                  <hi>But gather the wheat into my barne;</hi> the wheat is
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:114709:87"/>bleſſed in the firſt fruits; but the tares, their lot is to be burned, they are nothing belonging to the firſt fruits to be bleſſed, and enſured in them; no man when he offered God his firſt fruits, deſired a bleſſing upon the tares and weeds that grew in his field, but upon the good Corne: as therefore wee deſire to have a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Reſurrection, let us labour to belong to the firſt fruits. It is ſtrange that we ſhould thinke, to continue nothing but very tares and ſtinking weeds in Gods field, and thinke at harveſt time to be carried home in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his barne, as the beſt Corne. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, however it prove with us, that many a tare and filthy weed may be brought home among the good Corne, and many a good eare of Corne left behind in the field; yet at that harveſt, the end of the world, not one tare in Gods field ſhall be brought home into his barn, nor one eare of good Corne left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind to rot in the field. Let us therefore ſtrive to belong unto the firſt fruits, if we look to be bleſſed in the firſt fruits;</p>
            </div>
            <div n="150" type="page">
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:114709:88"/>
               <p>Secondly, If Chriſt be riſen <hi>as the firſt fruits,</hi> then let this confirme all them that belong unto the firſt fruits, in the aſſured bleſſed hope of their undoubted glorious Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; if the pooreſt deſpiſed mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Chriſts body ſhall not riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to glory, then Chriſt himſelfe is yet in the power of death, death gnawes upon him; It is the Apoſtle himſelfe that is thus bold; <hi>But if there be no Reſurrection from the dead,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.13.</note> 
                  <hi>then is Chriſt not riſen;</hi> the Head is not in Heaven, if any of the members ſhall for ever rot in the earth. Obſerve how ſtill the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture makes the bleſſed hope that is in us of our Reſurrections, to reſt and build it ſelfe upon Chriſts Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection;<note place="margin">Job. 19.25.26.</note> ſo Job, <hi>I know that my Redeemer liveth</hi> (is one that death hath no power over) <hi>and that he ſhall ſtand at the latter day upon the earth;</hi> and what then Job? what if thou knoweſt that? why, I know then that I ſhall not alwayes be wormes meat; but <hi>though after my skin wormes deſtroy this body, yet in my fleſh ſhall I ſee God;</hi> So the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:114709:88"/>having prayed that God would give the <hi>Epheſians</hi> enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned minds, to know the excellency of the happineſs that awaits them in Heaven, in theſe words, <hi>That yee may know what is the hope of his calling,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 1.18</note> 
                  <hi>and what the riches of the glory of his inheritance in the Saints;</hi> Leſt they ſhould thinke, But how ſhould wee ever attaine this hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, wee poore mortall corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible creatures, that dayly dy, and rot and putrify in the grave, and no ſigne of any ſuch enſuing glory? therefore he prayes withall, that they may know the greatneſs of Gods power in raiſing up Chriſt from the dead, as an aſſurance that he will alſo raiſe up them; <hi>And that ye may know what is the exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing greatneſs of his power to us ward who believe, according to the working of his mighty power which he wrought in Chriſt when he raiſed him from the dead;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 19.20.</note> becauſe as it follows, <hi>he raiſed up Chriſt to be the Head over all things to his Church which is his body, the fulneſs of him which
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:114709:89"/>filleth all in all;</hi> and therefore Chriſt is maimed and imperfect without his body; His body there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doubtles ſhal be aſſumed at laſt to him, body and head to make one perfect man, and one full Chriſt; <hi>Till we all come in the unity of the faith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 4.13.</note> 
                  <hi>and of the knowledge of the Son of God, unto a perfect man,</hi> &amp;c. what firmer hope therefore of our Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, then that wee are thus to be the fulneſs of Chriſt, who ſhould otherwiſe be a maimed Chriſt, an imperfect Chriſt, a halfe Chriſt, a head without a body? Further, for this point makes that, which the Apoſtle hath;<note place="margin">Phil. 3.10.</note> 
                  <hi>That I may know him, and the power of his Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction;</hi> and the power of his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection to me ward, to raiſe mee up alſo by an influence of the head upon the members; after all my fellowſhip with him in his ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings;<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.21.</note> 
                  <hi>Who by him do believe in God that raiſed him up from the dead, and gave him glory, that your faith and hope might be in God,</hi> ſc. nothing doubting, but that he
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:114709:89"/>would alſo raiſe you up, having raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him up your firſt fruits;<note place="margin">Rev. 1.18.</note> 
                  <hi>I am he that liveth, and was dead, and have the keyes of Hell and of death:</hi> have the keyes; he ſlipt not out onely himſelfe deceiving the keeper, but he came out powerfully with keyes in his hand, to let out alſo whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever of his he would; he did not indeed as <hi>Samſon</hi> did with the door of the gate of the City Gaza, carry away the door and all, that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever would might go forth, but onely tooke away the keyes of the door to let out and lock in ſtill whom he would:</p>
               <p>Thirdly, If Chriſt be riſen <hi>as the firſt fruits,</hi> then let this comfort us againſt the feare of death, if we reckon of a day wherein he that dyed for us and roſe again, will for that which is ſowne in corruption, raiſe it again in incorruption which is ſowne in diſhonour, raiſe it in glory; ſown in weakneſs, raiſe it in power; which is ſowne a naturall body, raiſe it a ſpirituall body; Why ſhould we much be afraid of death? death do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s but ſpoil us of
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:114709:90"/>our rags to give us robes, does but pull downe our old ruinous houſe, to reare up a new one, and a ſtately one, in the roome; <hi>We know that if our earthly houſe of this tabernacle were diſſolved,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.1.</note> 
                  <hi>we have a building of God, a houſe not made with hands;</hi> he that now fears death much, hath but either a little faith, or an ill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; and no marvaile if theſe two be afraid to dye; the one look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at death as an end of all his hopes; and the other as the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of all his miſery. But a good faith and a good conſcience will not feare that which it knows can neither hold it, nor hurt it; it knows that Chriſt is riſen as the firſt fruits, and it knows that it belongs to thoſe firſt fruits, it knows what that means;<note place="margin">John 6.39.</note> 
                  <hi>This is the Fathers will that of all which he hath given me, I ſhould loſe nothing, but ſhould raiſe it up again at the laſt day.</hi> And that; <hi>and if Chriſt be in you the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is dead becauſe of ſin,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.10.</note> 
                  <hi>but the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is life becauſe of righteouſneſs.</hi> And that;<note place="margin">Heb. 2.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Foraſmuch then as the
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:114709:90"/>children are partakers of fleſh and blood; he alſo himſelfe likewiſe tooke part of the ſame; that through death he might deſtroy him that had the power of death, the Divell;</hi> He knowes, that that which was ſpoken in a figure to the Jews, ſhall in the very letter be performed to him and all Chriſts members;<note place="margin">Eſay 26.19.</note> 
                  <hi>Thy dead men ſhall live together, with my dead bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſhall they ariſe; awake and ſing yee that dwell in duſt,</hi> &amp;c. and that which was a parable to them ſhall be a truth to the Saints; That the valley of dry bones that were very dry,<note place="margin">Ezek. 37.5.</note> the four winds ſhall blow upon them, and breath ſhall come into them, and they ſhall live, and ſtand up upon their feet an exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing great army: he knowes that that of <hi>Eſdras</hi> though it be Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryphall writing, yet it is Canonicall truth,<note place="margin">2 Eſd. 4.40.42.43.</note> 
                  <hi>Go thy way to a woman with childe, when ſhe hath fulfilled her nine moneths, if her wombe may keepe the birth any longer within her. For as ſhee that is with childe, haſteth to eſcape the neceſſitie of the travell,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:114709:91"/>ſo do theſe places haſte to deliver thoſe things that are committed unto them. That which thou deſireſt to ſee, ſhall be ſhewed thee from the beginning.</hi> and therefore if Chriſt be riſen the firſt fruits; what need I feare that that can neither hold me long, nor hurt me at all; that can neither end my hopes, nor can begin my miſeries?</p>
               <p>Fourthly, If Chriſt be riſen <hi>as the firſt fruits;</hi> then let this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort us againſt immoderate griefe and ſorrow for the death of friends; Why ſhould we immoderately grieve for the death of friends, whoſe death for their Souls is their preſent gaine; and for their bodies but onely a caſting of the ſeed into the ground to rot and reſt there for a while, that it may ſprout and ſpring up a farre more glorious bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, greene and freſh, and a goodlier body then it fell in, as is intimated here in verſe 37? <hi>And that which thou ſoweſt, thou ſoweſt not that body which ſhall be,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but God giveth it a body as it pleaſeth him;</hi> a greene<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="157" facs="tcp:114709:91"/>and freſh, a ſtatelyer and goodlyer body by farre then it was ſowne: and ſo for their Soul, death is their preſent gaine, if ſo be they can ſay with <hi>Paul, to me to live is Chriſt;</hi> for then it will follow,<note place="margin">Phil. 1.21.</note> 
                  <hi>to me to dy is gaine.</hi> Againe, except it be no gaine to be delivered out of a ſinfull and miſerable body; yea, a ſinfull and miſerable world, and carried into a holy and happy place, where ſin and miſery never peept in; It is our weakneſs and errour to thinke of our friends departed, <hi>as Jacob</hi> of <hi>Joſeph; Joſeph</hi> was in great honour in Egypt, and <hi>Jacob</hi> when he ſaw his bloodied coat, thought that ſurely an evill beaſt had devoured him, and <hi>Joſeph</hi> was not; but <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi> what bids he his brethren tell their Father to comfort him? <hi>You ſhall tell my Father of all my glory in Egypt.</hi> So wee, when wee ſee the bloodied coats of our friends as 'twere,<note place="margin">Gen. 45.9. 2 Cor. 5.4.</note> their dead bodies, I meane the garments of the Soul; we are ready to thinke that death, that evill beaſt hath made an end of
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:114709:92"/>them, and they are not; <hi>but tell my Father,</hi> &amp;c. So let us thinke of all the glory that they have in Heaven, and be comforted. Why ſhould we therefore immoderately grieve for our friends; whoſe death (for their Souls) is their preſent gaine, &amp;c? Wee that do ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderately grieve for the death of our friends, do we not mind what is the firſt thing uſed to be read at their burials; <hi>I am the Reſurrection and the life?</hi> and while the earth is caſt upon the body; <hi>Foraſmuch as it hath pleaſed,</hi> &amp;c. do we not mind theſe things? If we mind theſe things, certainly we have either little faith in us to believe the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Reſurrection of them that dy in Chriſt, or little hope in us to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade us that this our friend is dead in Chriſt, or little patience in us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the good will and providence of God wiſely ordering all things. If it be impatience in us, let us conſider <hi>Job,</hi> and what he ſaid, when among other things God had taken away his ſeven Sons and three daughters
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:114709:92"/>at once;<note place="margin">Job. 1.21.</note> 
                  <hi>The Lord gave and the Lord taketh away; Bleſſed be the name of the Lord.</hi> If it be becauſe that we have little hope that our friends are dead in Chriſt; why do we not then grieve for them, when wee ſee that our friends do not live in Chriſt? this griefe would be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, it would make us ſeeke their amendment. If laſtly, it be becauſe we have little faith in us to believe the glorious Reſurrection of them that dye in Chriſt; Let us conſider that if Chriſt be riſen the third day, then all that dy in Chriſt ſhall as undoubtedly riſe the laſt day; <hi>If we believe</hi> (ſayes the Apoſtle) <hi>that Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus dyed and roſe againe, even ſo them alſo which ſleep in Chriſt will God bring with him alſo;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.14.</note> If therefore Chriſt be riſen, &amp;c. their graves are but their beds to reſt their wearied bones in a while, till the day of the Lord dawne, and that great trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet ſound to waken them out of their ſleep; and who now that loves one another dearlyeſt, mournes when he bids him Good
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:114709:93"/>night, to go lye downe in his bed till next morning?</p>
               <p>Fifthly, If Chriſt be riſen <hi>as the firſt fruits;</hi> Let this comfort us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the preſent frailties and weakneſſes and vileneſs of theſe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of ours; bodies that are ſo ſoone puling and complaining for a little exceſſe of cold or heat, a little defect of meat or drinke; bodies that are ſo ſoone wearied, and tyred out with a little labour and pains in the Courſe of ones calling; bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies that are ſo often vexing us with cramps and aches and ſundry ſickneſſes; bodies that are ſoone withering and waxing old and mouldring away; bodies every way ſo vile, that ſome have irked to have any pictures made of their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, as but the picture of their ſhame; and indeed, were it not that they are our own bodies, and that every one have bodies alike, they would ſoone be ſeene how irk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome they are; but if Chriſt be ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, &amp;c. theſe corruptibles ſhall put on incorruption, and theſe mortalls
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:114709:93"/>ſhall put on immortality; and thus <hi>Job</hi> comforted himſelfe when he was ſo ſtruck with ſores and boils from the ſole of the foot to the crowne of the head, and ſo ſpent and waſted in his body with the heat and inflammation of thoſe burning boils that he was even eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped with the skin of his teeth; had no more left almoſt upon that poore carcaſſe of his, then on his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry teeth, where is nothing at all; yet being in that caſe, he thus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted himſelfe; <hi>I know that my Redeemer liveth; and though after my skin</hi> (as having almoſt nothing now on this back, but a little withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red skin) <hi>worms deſtroy this body</hi> (this poore torne, tattered, rent, ſpent carcaſſe of mine) <hi>yet in my fleſh ſhall I ſee God.</hi> And thus St. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo intimates comfort againſt the vileneſs and abjectneſs of theſe bodyes of ours, by conſidering the glory they ſhall have at the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection;<note place="margin">Phil. 3.21.</note> 
                  <hi>who ſhall change our vile bodies that they may be faſhioned like unto his glorious body,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="162" facs="tcp:114709:94"/>
               <p>Sixthly, If Chriſt be riſen <hi>as the firſt fruits,</hi> &amp;c. then what thankes owe we to God and the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt for ſo great a bleſſing, ſo great a bleſſing as affords this comfort againſt all the preſent frailties and vileneſs of our bodies, againſt all exceſſive greife for the death of our friends, againſt all tormenting anxious feares for our owne deaths; as being aſſured that Chriſt is not onely riſen from the dead, but riſen as the firſt fruits to enſure the glorious Reſurrection of all thoſe that belong to him? This uſe of thankfulneſs for ſo great a bleſſing, the Apoſtle makes; <hi>Bleſſed be the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.3.</note> 
                  <hi>which hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten us againe to a lively hope by the Reſurrection of Jeſus from the dead.</hi> And here St. <hi>Paul</hi> in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Chapter, <hi>O death, where is thy ſting, O grave where is thy victory! Thanks be to God which giveth us the victory through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> And indeed, he that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiders what death is backed with, ſin
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:114709:94"/>and the unalterable Law of God, can eaſily be moved to thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for victory over it through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and his death and Reſurrection.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, if Chriſt be riſen <hi>as the firſt fruits,</hi> &amp;c. then let theſe bodies of ours be ſacred and holy to him here, which we looke ſhould be glorious and happy in him hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; in him as glorified members of him a more glorious head; he will never make him a glorious member that is not firſt a holy member; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver deliver him from the bondage of death, that does not ſeeke firſt to be delivered of ſin; never deliver him from the corruption of the grave that does not ſeeke firſt to be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from the corruption of luſt: If it were poſſible that any member of Chriſt in Heaven ſhould either be a ſinfull member, or a poor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible member, ſooner ſhould it be a poor contemptible member, then a ſinfull member; our Saviour ſometimes here upon earth had a vile contemptible body, but never
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:114709:95"/>a ſinfull body; looke we therefore that theſe bodyes of ours ſhould be happy and glorious in him hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? let them be ſacred and holy to him here; Think with thy ſelfe, when gluttony and drunkenneſs diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honours thy body, is this drunken body fit to be a member of Chriſts glorious body? when filthyneſs and uncleanneſs defiles thy body; is this filthy body fit to be a member, &amp;c? thinke with thy ſelfe when violence, bribery, injuſtice, cozenage, and trading Legerdemanie cleaves to thy hand; is this hand, fit to be a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Chriſts glorious body, &amp;c? when pride, envy, avarice, adultery ſits in thy eye, is this eye fit to be a member of Chriſts glorious body, &amp;c? when profane, and curſed ſpeaking, horrible ſwearing, ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering backbiting, &amp;c. furres thy tongue, is this filthy furred tongue, fit to be a member of Chriſts glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious body, &amp;c? How does the Apoſtle reaſon againſt the abuſing of the body by the ſinne of fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Now the body is not for forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:114709:95"/>but for the Lord;</hi> and is it fit that that body that is the Lords body, &amp; looks to be raiſed up a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious member of him already a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious head, is it fit that body ſhould be for filthyneſs and fornication? If we will needs ſo diſhonour our ſelves as to make our bodyes the members of harlots, let us know that Chriſt will not ſo diſhonour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe as to make the members of harlots his own members. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt be riſen as the firſt fruits, &amp;c. he will not have, like <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzars</hi> image, the head to be of gold, and any of the members, though the very feet, the loweſt, to be of baſe clay and dirt.</p>
               <p>Eighthly, If Chriſt be riſen <hi>as the firſt fruit;</hi> then let us be bold to venture theſe bodies of ours, be it unto the death, in behalfe of him and his glory, who dyed for us and roſe againe to enſure the glorious Reſurrection of theſe bodies; our bodies are not ſo ſure our owne now that we have them, and are cloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with them; as when they are off
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:114709:96"/>at his bidding: he does but lay them up in a ſure wardrobe, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore us them again, far better then we doft them off: ſo much deceived were thoſe heatheniſh perſecutours, that burning the Chriſtians, gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up the aſhes of their bodies and threw them into the river <hi>Rhone</hi> to be carried away, who knowes whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that they might make the Chriſtians without all hopes of the Reſurrection; but little knew they that they had a head in Heaven that as thoſe bones by prophecying came together bone to his bone, ſo by but ſpeaking unto them could make all thoſe aſhes come together, were they never ſo ſcattered with the four winds;<note place="margin">Euſeb. 5.</note> ſee how this, (the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurement of our glorious Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions in and by Chriſt) is made a ſpeciall ground and motive in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for our ſufferings;<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.14. Act. 20.20. 1 Cor. 15.32. Gal. 6.12.</note> 
                  <hi>ſo we believe, and therefore ſpeake,</hi> ſpeake without concealment of any part of the truth of the Goſpel, though thereby we procure our ſelves great perſecution at the hands of the Jews: and what
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:114709:96"/>is the ground of his boldneſs? <hi>Knowing that he which raiſed up the Lord Jeſus, ſhall raiſe up us alſo by Jeſus;</hi> ſo,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.13.</note> Exhorting <hi>Timothy</hi> to conſtancy in the Goſpel whatſoever befell upon it,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.8.</note> upon what ground does he it? <hi>ſc.</hi> this, <hi>Remember that Jeſus Chriſt of the ſeed of David was raiſed from the dead,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 2.8.</note> &amp;c. ſo the Lord exhorting the Church of <hi>Smyrna</hi> to endure tribulation for his names ſake, upon what ground does he it? <hi>ſc.</hi> this, <hi>theſe things ſaith the Firſt and the Laſt, which was dead and is alive;</hi> &amp;c. And ſo though you dye in his cauſe, feare not, he will make you alive againe; if therefore Chriſt be riſen as, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Ninthly, If Chriſt be riſen <hi>as the firſt fruits,</hi> let us while we are in theſe bodies of ours, be conſtant and abundant in all good works; knowing that our labour none of it all ſhall be loſt, but a day ſhal come, when if we could be ſorry for any thing, it ſhould be eſpecially for this, that we have ſlugged it ſo much in the work of godlineſs. <hi>Let
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:114709:97"/>not thine heart envy ſinners;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 23.17, 18.</note> 
                  <hi>for ſurely there is an end</hi> (even that end 1 Cor. 15.24.) <hi>and thine expectation ſhall not be cut off;</hi> And <hi>have hope towards God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 24.15, 16.</note> 
                  <hi>that there ſhall be a Reſurrection, &amp;c. and herein do I exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe my ſelfe, to have a conſcience alwayes void of offence, both towards God and man.</hi> And here in this Chapter, after the Apoſtle hath ſufficiently proved Chriſts Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and alſo our glorious Reſurrection in him, This is the very uſe he makes of it in the laſt verſe;<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Therefore, my beloved, be ye ſtedfaſt, ſetled, grounded, confirm'd,</hi> in the infallible faith of Chriſts and your Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections; <hi>and unmoveable, not onely ſetled,</hi> but unmoveably ſetled, that nothing be able to ſhake you from that ſtedfaſtneſs, not the violence of Tyrants perſecuting you, not the ſubtilty of Philoſophers ſeeking to cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumvent you; and if you continue thus ſtedfaſt, and unmoveable in this your faith, what will then follow, but that you ſhould abound, not be ſpare and ſcanty, but abound; and that not when you are ready to lay downe theſe bodies of yours onely, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes: <hi>Abounding alwayes in the work of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:114709:97"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
